<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons of assise the one intituled A prohibition of reuenge, the other, A sword of maintenance : preached at two seuerall times, before the right worshipfull iudges of assise, and gentlemen assembled in Hertford, for the execution of iustice, and now published / by W. Westerman ...</title>
            <author>Westerman, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14975</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23371838</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23371838</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26599</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14975)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26599)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1805:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons of assise the one intituled A prohibition of reuenge, the other, A sword of maintenance : preached at two seuerall times, before the right worshipfull iudges of assise, and gentlemen assembled in Hertford, for the execution of iustice, and now published / by W. Westerman ...</title>
                  <author>Westerman, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 66, [2], 55 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.B. for Gregory Seaton, and are to be solde at his shop vnder Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The sworde of maintenance" has special t.p. and separate pagination.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁸ F², ²A-C⁸ ²D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XII, 19 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Amos V, 15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26599:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26599:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TWO SERMONS OF ASSISE: The one intituled; <hi>A prohibition of Reuenge:</hi> The other, <hi>A Sword of Maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached at two ſeuerall times, <hi>before the Right worſhipfull Iudges</hi> of Aſſiſe, and Gentlemen aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Hertford, for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtice: and now publiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By W. Weſterman, Miniſter of the word, in Sandridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Printed by R. B. for <hi>Gregory</hi> Seaton, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop vnder Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:26599:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>MVNIFICENTIA REGIA. 1715.</p>
                  <p>GEORGIVS D.G. MAG. BR <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ET HIB. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> FD.</p>
                  <byline>J. Pin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſculp</byline>
                  <figDesc>bookplate</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26599:2"/>
            <head>To the Right worſhipfull <hi>and worthie Gentlemen, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Rafe Coningsbye, and maſter Pope Blunt, Eſquiers, and in Commiſſion of the Peace for the Countie of Hertf. and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of S. Albans, W. W. wiſheth all increaſe of heauenly wiſdome, to the glorie of God, the profite of their Countrie, and the ſaluation of their owne ſoules.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T your requeſts, in your ſeuerall Sheriualties (Right worſhipfull) I preached theſe two ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: where I truſt the Lord gaue a bleſſing, to the fruit of my barren and vnworthie lippes. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the most part of Auditors heare ſermons, as Trauailers, by the lawe, might vſe Grapes: that is: <hi>eate ſome</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 23. 25</note> 
               <hi>for the preſent time, but cary none away with them:</hi> and for that our
<pb facs="tcp:26599:3"/> Lord and Sauiour teacheth ſuch fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie in feaſts of ſmall preparation, that the <hi>fragments ſhould be gathered</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn. 6. 12.</note> 
               <hi>vp, and nothing loſt:</hi> I haue thought it not amiſſe, to preſſe out the liquour of theſe my grapes, and preſent the reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them, as it were after the feaſt, in this basket of leaues: for a more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall vſe, and longer continuaunce. If the remaynes ſeeme greater then the former prouiſion, impute it to Gods bleſsing, that ſuffereth no decrements, nor want at his feaſtes: and to the ſhort allowance of tyme, wherewith my wordes (but not my ſenſe) were aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſtinted at the first deliuerie. In ſuch earnest buſineſſe, when there is no ſurplus of time to bee borrowed, we holde it lawfull to temporize: not quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſpirit, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueying the ſtreams
<pb facs="tcp:26599:3"/> of our words within narrow banks: after which ſort, they may be more fruitfull (the Lorde aſsiſting) then if they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowed, all without boundes or meaſure. But howſoeuer then, theſe exerciſes were abridged by the hower, yet now in the writing, I haue giuen them more free vent, and libertie, where euerie man may bee the caruer of his owne time, in hearing and reading. And in this maner nowe publiſhed, I ſende them abroade, vnder your names and tytles (Right worſhipfull) that they may be, not onelie a pledge of my good will to you both, vnited in one Epistle, as yee are in loue; and in loue like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 20. 17. 2. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and <hi>Ionathan:</hi> but alſo giue te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of that commendable order in your graue aſſemblies, where I perceiued both Iudges and Gentlemen, beginning
<pb facs="tcp:26599:4"/> their affaires, with the firſt fruits of their knees, eares, hearts, and tongues conſecrated to God, and directing the reſt of their proceedings accordingly, in wiſedome, and iuſtice. In this looſe and prophane age, wherin too many make an Idole of their priuate fancie, and bleſſe themſelues in their mother witte (the <hi>moſte baſe Idolatrie of all others,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de vera elig. ca. 38.</note> ſaith <hi>Auſten</hi>) It is a comfort yet, that the Cedars, and men of greateſt note, will beautifie Gods ſeruice with theyr worthie examples, as they ſtrengthen iudgement with their Authoritie. The deligent execution of iudgement in ciuil cauſes, is without doubt an acceptable ſeruice to God. For which purpoſe, both Iudges, &amp; Rulers are commanded to be wiſe, and learned, that in the ſame they may ſerue the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet not onely as ciuil
<pb facs="tcp:26599:4"/> Politicians, but as holy Chriſtians with feare and trembling. And therefore they<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> muſt <hi>kiſſe the ſonne,</hi> leaſt he be angrie, and bende the knees of their wiſdome, power, &amp; authoritie, to the name of him firſt, that is preſident ouer the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the gods on earth. The heathens neuer durſt attempt any matter of great importance, without inuocation on their gods, and ſome ſolemne inauguration, or ſacrifice, performed by their prieſts, and wizards; to get a forehand bleſsing to their actions. Euen amongſt them it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med abſurd, and arrogant, to commence graue enterpryſes, without calling a greater power to their aſsistaunce: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome did attribute ſo much to their owne wiſedome, proweſſe, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, that they thought praiers were for ſimple wretches, and fooles, as <hi>Aiax</hi> (like
<pb facs="tcp:26599:5"/> an Atheiſt) vaunted: <hi>Aliorum eſt vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cthon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rat. de precat.</note> 
               <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o iuuante, &amp;c.</hi> Other coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie fellowes may obtaine victorie by the helpe of God, but ſuch as he could do well enough without him. Yet ſuch were accompted moſt miſerable, euen of thoſe that had onelie a generall glimſe of an vnknowne God: and therefore <hi>Homer</hi> at all hard aſſaies, ſheweth how great, &amp; ſmall, did enterpriſe nothing without ſome ſupplication to the gods. As for the auncient <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> they had their <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 10.</note> with <hi>trumpets</hi> to go before them; <hi>Prieſtes</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> aſsiſtant in all<note place="margin">1. Sam. 13. 13</note> difficult occaſions. When <hi>Saul</hi> left <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> he proued himſelfe a foole, though hee offered a ſelfe-will ſacrifice to the Lord. And what became of the penne of the <hi>Scribes,</hi> or the wiſdome of the wiſe, when they leaned to their owne fancies?
<pb facs="tcp:26599:5"/> 
               <hi>The pen</hi> (ſaith Ieremy <hi>became vain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>the wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are aſhamed, afraid, &amp; taken, for lo: they haue reiected the word of the Lord, and what wiſdom is in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> But the practiſe in thoſe your aſſemblies, declare your reuerence to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſes, which to your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendations and gods glory are continued: the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of heauen being firſt vnfolded, &amp; the Commiſſion from the next ſupreame Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernor, afterward being read, that both your authoritie from heauen, and earth, may giue the Iudges confidence in their proceedings, &amp; good ſucceſſe in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations. In that place at two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times I was a witnes of the generall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of many worthy gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the furthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of peace, iuſtice, &amp; good order: but I haue had dayly experience in your ſelues, &amp; ſom others about vs, with what ſingular
<pb facs="tcp:26599:6"/> care and dexteritie, you haue managed the weightie affaires, both of your Prince and country, whenſoeuer you haue beene emploied, by commiſsion from the one, or petition from the other. Neither haue your publike employments withdrawne you from the exerciſe of priuate vertues: your delight in holie exerciſes is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, by your diligent repaire vnto them, your affabilitie, and kindneſſe appeareth in the courteous carriage of your ſelues towardes all men that deſerue not the contrarie. Which perſonall qualities are alſo graced with a diligent reformation of your followers: <hi>a matter of greater</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic. dicto Traiano.</note> 
               <hi>magnificence</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plinie) then for a man to reforme himſelfe.</hi> Whence it was that the Queene of <hi>Saba</hi> was not onelie in admiration of <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. King. 10. 5.</note> and anſwers; but alſo of the ſitting
<pb facs="tcp:26599:6"/> of his ſeruants, and the order and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of his attendants. To confirme and encourage you in this courſe of vertue, ye haue had both domeſticall, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour examples, whereof ſome haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their race, others remaine ſtill, not forgetfull of their Countrie by priuate occaſions, or greater preferments. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst whom I may regiſter theſe two worthy &amp; ancient ſtandards, ſir <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Cocke,</hi> and ſir <hi>Philip Butler,</hi> knights of eſpeciall marke, and accompt, ſuch as ſince my remembrance haue flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the Courts of the Lords houſe, and yeelded much excellent ſeruice to their Prince, ſuccour to their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, and ſhadow to the Preachers, and miniſters of the truth. Neither is the laſt of theſe qualities to be the leaſt regarded, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie amongſt vs, where the miniſters
<pb facs="tcp:26599:7"/> are prouided of maintenaunce, but as yonger brethren, hauing liuings for the moſt part like the <hi>Amazonites,</hi> giuing ſucke but of one breaſt, the other being diſeaſed with a Wolfe, or quite cut off with an Impropriation. For who ſeeth not how euerie Bramble is readie to ſcratch them that creepe low? euerie co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde hartned to ſtrike him that may not ſtrike again? I ſpeake not this for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiencie of want, or iniuries, or to plead an irregularitie to priuiledge any cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in vs: for wee haue learned both to be abaſed, &amp; to abound, to turne our cheekes to the ſmiter: and giue for a<note place="margin">Philip. 4. 10. Math. 5.</note> need the coat of a poore vicaridge, to him that by law can take away the cloake of of our parſonage. But ſo long as the Lord maintaineth the crowne vpon the head of his annointed handmaid, &amp; continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:26599:7"/> our gracious Prince nurſe royall of the Goſpel, &amp; mother of peace: we are to expect ſafely vnder ſuch as you (Right worſhipfull) being hir hands, &amp; wings of defence, as ſhe is the Angel of God vpon the earth for the preſeruation of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets &amp; people. And I muſt confeſſe, that as the Lord hath planted this barren iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction with many fruitfull vines: ſo haue they receiued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time much comfort &amp; aſsiſtance in their miniſterie, by you the religious gentlemen of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and countenaunce, wherein you giue teſtimony thai you feare the Lord, whoſe lowly ambaſſadors you kindly entertain. And his true feare is the only grain, that ſetteth a perfect glaſſe, and a liuely tinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture vpon all other wordly reſpectes and colours: which ſhall flouriſh, when <hi>Nimrods Babel, Abſolons pillar,</hi> &amp; all gorgeous buildings, with the names
<pb facs="tcp:26599:8"/> of their founders ſhal lie in the duſt. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amongeſt theſe comforts receyued, toward the encouragement of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters here abouts, may I forget the tender regard of that reuerend father, placed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs, now L. B. of Lond. whoſe entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was in much fatherly kindneſſe towards vs: not in any hard exactions, coloured with beneuolence, but rather in forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of auntient duties; ſince when he hath declared his continuall care, by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe cautions giuen for our gentle and courteous vſage: beſide the preuention of ſome late expenſes, and payments, that elſe-where, the meaneſt liuings taſted deepely of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> All which temporall encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements, being ſupplies of ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to a meane eſtate, we thankefully a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cept, as at the handes of God, thereby acknowledging our ſelues deepely bound
<pb facs="tcp:26599:8"/> to diſtill our ſpirits, and ſtudies into ſuch wine of comfort, as may againe cheare both God and men. In the depth of which deſire, I the moſt vntimely ſlippe in the vineyard, haue tendered theſe two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as an after gleaning of grapes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſſe of learning: the licor wherof if it hath any wateriſh, or earthly we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, impute it to the caſke: if it haue any ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall relliſhe, or ſweet ſauour, yeelde the praiſe and glorie to God, who is able to turne our weake water, into wine of ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g conſolation; whereof I wiſh the perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fruition, to your ſelues as to mine own ſoule. And further deſiring the Lord of his abundance, to multiplie his graces ſpirituall &amp; temporall, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you &amp; your poſteritie for euer: I hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly take my leaue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord, William Weſterman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26599:9"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26599:9"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>Auenge not your ſelues (dearely beloued)<note place="margin">Text <hi>Rom. 12. 19.</hi>
                        </note> but giue place vnto wrath: for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: vengeaunce is mine, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paye, ſayth the Lord.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſt wiſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Lord</hi> &amp; Law-giuer of <hi>Iſraell</hi> (Right <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull</hi> and right <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Audience</hi>) orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that the ſonnes of Aaron with their <hi>ſiluer Trumpets,</hi> ſhould ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out, as well the ſommons vnto the <hi>ciuill aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Numb. 10. 2. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>of peace,</hi> and religious exerciſes: as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larum to battayle,</hi> and warlike enterpriſes. The ſame <hi>Lord</hi> beeing our <hi>God</hi> ſtill, requireth the ſubſtance of thoſe ceremonious ſhadowes in our ſolemnities. For <hi>yee</hi> are <hi>his</hi> people; we are the <hi>Leuites:</hi> his two <hi>Teſtaments</hi> are the two ſiluer <hi>Trumpets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> the diſtinction of ſounds is pricked downe before vs in his booke of truth, whoſe direct wee are to ſing after, ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding out ſometime doctrine of inſtruction, ſometime of reproofe, ſometime of comfort, ſetting it ſometimes to the heads and rulers, ſometimes to the meaner ſort, ſometimes to peace, ſometimes to warr, as the Lord ſheweth occaſion, and the ſpirit giueth vtterance. Now becauſe I am at this preſent, though of my
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26599:10"/> ſelfe an earthen pitcher, yet called to vtter ſome certaine voyce out of theſe ſiluer trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, that all ſorts of Auditors heere aſſembled may reuerently, and in the feare of God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelues to be Actors in this entended ſeruice: I haue made choyſe of this Text to be the keye whereunto I may ſet my tune: wherein the holie Ghoſt by ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a retreate vnto all quarrellers, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffes, intending priuate reuenge, or hamme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring miſchiefe in their hearts. For as in the former part of this Chapter, hee vſed all ſweet inducements vnto loue, and peace, and all good arguments to diſſwade from haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe of minde, ambition, ſelfe-conceipt, being the only ſparkes that fire mens affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and hinder that peace which wee ſhould keepe <hi>with all men, if it be poſſible, and lye in vs:</hi> ſo now as though hee perceaued mens heartes burning, theyr deſires ſwelling, theyr mouthes raging, theyr handes threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, theyr daggers drawne, and the peace in daunger to be broken, he ſteppeth foorth in the middeſt, as a bleſſed peace-maker, and draweth out the ſword of the ſpirit to take vp all quarrels, &amp; preuent all miſchiefes, after this manner: <hi>Auenge not your ſelues (dearely beloued) but giue place to wrath: for it is written &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:26599:10"/>
                  <p>This ſeemes to be a Writ from aboue: and it is to be ſerued by vs the Meſſengers of the Lord, vpon you his people, that by meanes of your Chriſtian profeſſion doe owe eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all obedience to the high court of heauen. If wee breake open this writ, wee ſhall perceiue the contentes thereof to be firſt <hi>A Prohibition</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Prohibition</note> 
                     <hi>of Reuenge: Auenge not your ſelues (dearely beloued) but giue place to wrath:</hi> ſecondly a <hi>Confirmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> by the Authoritie of ſcripture. <hi>For</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Confirmati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>it is written: vengeaunce is mine, I will repay, ſayth the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Reuenge is the puniſhment of iniuries, and<note place="margin">The Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</note> the redreſſe of wrongs; the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to whom this puniſhment and <hi>vengeaunce</hi> belongeth: <hi>it is mine ſaith the Lord, I will repay,</hi> by my ſelfe or my ſubſtitutes; therefore <hi>Auenge not yourſelues,</hi> intrude not into my throne, foreſtall not my right; but rather giue place to myne ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, let mans anger yeeld to Gods wrath; mans impotencie to gods power: mans par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie to Gods Iuſtice; mans ſecret conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie to the publike Iudgement eſtabliſhed by God himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Reuenge</hi> therefore that is by this <hi>Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> remoued, is <hi>priuate:</hi> ſuch as receiuing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries offered without <hi>right,</hi> repayeth them againe without <hi>Law.</hi> The reuenge, &amp; redreſſe of wrongs warranted vnto vs, is the wrath &amp; vengeance of the Lord: either mediatly to be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26599:11"/> executed by his Miniſters ordayned to take vengeaunce of euill doers: or elſe immediatly by the Lord himſelfe, where the ſword of the Magiſtrate is too ſhort, or the hand too ſlack, to ſmite the malefactor.</p>
                  <p>The chiefeſt doubt remayneth in this word <hi>Wrath,</hi> to the which wee are to <hi>giue place:</hi> for ſome haue interpreted it of mans <hi>Wrath,</hi> not Gods: ſome of our owne wrath wherein wee<note place="margin">Imbroſ. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>. lib. 1. C. 12</note> are <hi>agents</hi> and feele our anger boyling, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to kindle in the boſome: theſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle vs to reſiſt anger at the firſt, or at the leaſt, to retyre our ſelues and giue backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the extremitie, and continuaunce of it: to let<note place="margin">Aretius.</note> ſlippe all occaſions of quarrell, and ſo to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get and forgiue, that wee eſchew all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocations, all motions or ſpeaches, that may renew the memorie of wrongs, or nouriſh the conceipt of iniuries and indignities: ſome againe expound it of mans wrath as it is in another, &amp; wherin he is the <hi>Patient:</hi> as though this were a <hi>Caueat</hi> to ſtay vs from laying <hi>ſticks</hi> vpon another mans <hi>fire:</hi> that wee blow not the coales, of another mans choler: that <hi>wee anſwere not a foole according to his fooliſhneſſe,</hi> nor an haſtie <hi>man according to his haſtineſſe:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactant. lib. 6. Inſtit. Cap. 18.</note> by that meanes <hi>adding oyle to his flame,</hi> or oyning our impatiencie with his iniuſtice.</p>
                  <p>But wee follow thoſe interpreters which with beſt warrant do vnderſtand this wrath
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26599:11"/> of <hi>Gods wrath,</hi> and the <hi>reuenge of iniquitie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Alhanaſ. irae diuinae. Auguſt <hi>in Pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 78. vindictai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quitatis. Thom. Iudicio diuino.</note> or his <hi>diuine Iudgement,</hi> and not of the anger either of the wrong dooer, or ſufferer? For notwithſtanding the ſenſe of the former be godly and ſomewhat to our purpoſe: yet this phraſe of <hi>giuing place,</hi> is not vſed in that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification affirmatiuely, but rather negatiuely: as (<hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſayth to the <hi>Epheſians) Giue no place to the diuell:</hi> and ſo in that ſenſe would hee haue ſaide heere, <hi>giue no place to wrath,</hi> if hee had vnderſtood it of the vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and wicked wrath of man, and not of the moſt lawfull and holie wrath of God. But I neede not make many wordes, let the <hi>Holie Ghoſt</hi> interpret it ſelfe, which by the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation</hi> brought from the <hi>Authoritie</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and the <hi>mouth</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> himſelfe, doth manifeſtly declare, that ſuch wrath is heere to be yeelded vnto, as the Lord claimeth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by the termes of vengeaunce and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence: the later whereof, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for the<note place="margin">Deut. 31. 35,</note> more certaintie, and clearer application ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth in the perſon of God, and action of his vengeaunce, <hi>I will repay.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now wee haue notice of the Authoritie wherewith this writ is confirmed, let vs ſerch the contents and meaning of the <hi>Prohibition,</hi> being directed from ſo great a Lord, vnder perill of our ſoules if wee obey not his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:26599:12"/>
                  <p>In this behold firſt the <hi>title</hi> wherewith S. <hi>Paul</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The title. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aint. Reaſons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orcinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em.</note> greeteth vs: which is moſt kinde and louing; <hi>Dearely beloued:</hi> ſecondly the <hi>reſtraint, Auenge not your ſelues:</hi> thirdly a <hi>direction; giue place to wrath.</hi> Fourthly: note how euery wotd of the <hi>prohibition</hi> is backed &amp; ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon implied, to diſſwade from priuate reuenge, and to draw to a patient abiding of the Lords leiſure, and an expectation of his iudgements to be executed.</p>
                  <p>Let vs firſt examine this amiable title, which<note place="margin">The title.</note> ſerueth as a ſweet ingredience to qualifie a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter medicine: <hi>Dearely beloued</hi> ſaith hee, as though he would proteſt before hand, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he reſiſted their affections, and croſſed their ſtubborne willes, by with-holding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, yet he did it for loue to their ſoules, and cure to the ſoares of their mindes. If we conſider the eſtate of Gods <hi>beloued</hi> people in this life, we ſhal finde that they haue neede of many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions and precepts of patience, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, firſt becauſe of their infirmities, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly becauſe of the continual reproches and wrongs which ſhall be offered vnto them. Gods beſt beloued are not ſo perfect and exact, but they are ſubiect to paſſions, and often reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1, Sam.</hi> 25. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> of Reuenge againſt their enimies: as, <hi>Dauid</hi> was marching to the deſtruction of <hi>Naball,</hi> for his churliſh anſwere, till <hi>Abigail</hi> meereth him, and with gracious words aſſwageth his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26599:12"/> And who ſeeth not; but the life of the beſt Chriſtians is a marke for all wicked men, and the diuell himſelfe to be continually darting at, and therefore euen to them, being <hi>Gods beloued</hi> is it neceſſarie to giue this <hi>Item: Dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued auenge not your ſelues.</hi> Beloued they were to whom <hi>Paul</hi> vttered this, as thoſe are that he are this firſt <hi>beloued</hi> of the Lord: ſecondly for the Lords ſake beloued of the miniſters of God. Will you then ſee what reaſons may bee drawne from this title, to keepe all Chriſtians<note place="margin">Reaſons from the title againſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge.</note> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuenge? Say you are diſquieted, repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, oppreſſed: Let this be your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, you are <hi>beloued</hi> of God, whoſoeuer hateth you: you are his dearlings, <hi>he tendreth your caſe, hee numbreth your haires, hee putteth your teares in his bottell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee are content to endure great daungers, for thoſe that wee know <hi>loue</hi> vs: to put vp many iniuries at the intreatie of our friendes: and who is a <hi>louer</hi> like the <hi>Lord,</hi> or a <hi>friend</hi> like him, which entreateth vs, and chargeth vs, not to <hi>Auenge our ſelues,</hi> not <hi>to reſiſt euill,</hi> but to commit our cauſes, and <hi>ſoules in well doing to</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>the Lord our faythfull Creator, and Reuenger.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe: thoſe whom wee <hi>loue</hi> wee imitate, and expreſſe in manners and behauiour: As <hi>God</hi> is our <hi>Father</hi> in <hi>Creation &amp; Adoption:</hi> ſo muſt we proue our ſelues to be his children in <hi>Imitation:</hi> but in nothing may wee better
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26599:13"/> declare who is our father, then as wee were <hi>beloued</hi> when wee were <hi>enemies:</hi> ſo to <hi>loue</hi> againe, and <hi>pray</hi> for our <hi>enimies</hi> when they haue wronged <hi>vs.</hi> Dyd our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt reuenge when hee was hurt?</hi> No: ſayth the <hi>Apoſtle, beeing reuiled hee reuiled not againe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pet. 2. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>beeing iniuried hee ſought no reuenge, when he ſuffered, hee threatned not, but committed it to him that iudgeth righteouſly. Thus doing hee left an example, that we ſhould follow his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteppes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>diuell</hi> when hee getteth audience, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a man how much hee is <hi>hated,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuried: but the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> being <hi>pure</hi> is alſo <hi>peaceable</hi> and telleth him how much hee is<note place="margin">Iam. 3. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>beloued,</hi> endeuoring to drowne all conceipt of mens ſpight and malice, in the depth of Gods <hi>loue</hi> ſet as a <hi>ſeale</hi> to his conſcience. And from this <hi>ground</hi> of Gods fauour and <hi>loue,</hi> he rayſeth an argument of charitie and kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to other: wherefore <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3. ſaith Saint<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>Paul; As the elect of God, holie and beloued put on the bowels of mercie, kindeneſſe, humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde, meekeneſſe, long ſuffering, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing one another, and forgiuing one another: as Chriſt forgaue you, euen ſo doe yee.</hi> For it is an <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Couenant</hi> beetweene God and our ſelues, rehearſed in our <hi>prayers,</hi> and <hi>parle</hi> with the <hi>Lord,</hi> that as wee are <hi>forgiuen</hi> our <hi>offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſes,</hi> ſo ſhould wee <hi>forgiue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:26599:13"/>
                  <p>If wee breake couenant, and forgiue not others: how can wee demaund performance at his hands, and not rather looke for ſuch <hi>meaſure</hi> as wee <hi>mete</hi> to others? When our <hi>Maſter</hi> remitteth <hi>ten thouſand talents,</hi> if wee bee ſtraight laced, and will not forgiue a trifle<note place="margin">Math. 18.</note> of ſome <hi>hundred pence,</hi> it is a token that our finall <hi>quietus eſt,</hi> is not ſigned by the Lord, but that hee will call vs backe to an after <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coning,</hi> to pay the <hi>vtmoſt farthing,</hi> or indeede lye by it for euer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dearely beloued,</hi> ſayth <hi>Paul,</hi> as of <hi>God,</hi> ſo <hi>beloued</hi> for <hi>his</hi> ſake of my <hi>ſelfe: I loue</hi> you and yet may not <hi>flatter you.</hi> What will many of our paynted <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſay to this? Surely, hee is not my <hi>friend,</hi> hee loues mee not, that would aduiſe mee to ſuffer this diſgrace, or put vp this iniurie: It is againſt my honour, my worſhip, ſay the greateſt, againſt my profit &amp; credit, ſay the meaner ſort: nay it is againſt my conſcience, (ſay many) to endure theſe wrongs: when alas it is luſt and concupiſcence,<note place="margin">Iam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. 1</note> not conſcience that fighteth in their members, and breedeth this diſquiet.</p>
                  <p>Are wee then beloued of the Lord, and of thoſe that are his deare children, though wee be maligned and hated, and oppreſſed of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? O let vs keepe this hauen of refuge, and ſuccour open, that when the world is a ſea of troubles raging againſt vs, wee may ſhoot our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26599:14"/> ſelues into the ſame: and giue backe into the comfortable armes of his loue. Let vs rather looſe our longing deſire of reuenge, then the fauour of that Lord, by whom we are ſo deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued.</p>
                  <p>Thus doth the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſweeten his<note place="margin">Prou. 27. 6.</note> ſharpe meſſage, like a louer, giuing <hi>a faythfull wound</hi> for health, and not for hurt: in a tender regarde to preſerue his clients (like a good counſaylour) in the euerlaſting poſſeſſion of their ſoules by patience. As <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo I would all <hi>Ambaſſadours</hi> of heauenly peace would keepe this note of loue, that one ſtring ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding right, might ſerue to ſet all the other in tune. And thus much for this ſweet <hi>title: Dearely beloued:</hi> which I deſire of the Lord may make ſuch melody in your hearts, at this preſent time, that all deſire of reuenge, and bitter paſſions of the minde aſſwaged, you may be tranſformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch ſincere keepers, counſaylours, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of peace, that this title may remaine for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer verified in your ſoules, <hi>Dearely beloued<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now foloweth the reſtraint, <hi>Auenge not your</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint.</note> 
                     <hi>ſelues. Reuenge</hi> is a raſh proceeding to the puniſhment of iniuries receaued, without law, without order, without authoritie. In euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate<note place="margin">Of reuenge by heart, tongue, and hand.</note> man there be three inſtruments readie to further this reuenge, the heart, the tongue, the hand.</p>
                  <p>Firſt is the heart prohibited from all pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26599:14"/> and deuiſe, or deſire of vengeaunce.<note place="margin">1. The heart.</note> For in the heart is the bottome and coare of this diſeaſe. There lurkes a roote of bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which if it be not ſtocked vp, will ſpring vp, and defile both mouth, and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Concupiſcence is the mother of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wicked impes, fathered by the diuell, and conceiued in the wombe of the heart, which muſt be ſtrangled in the byrth: or elſe like the vipers broode, they deſtroy the wombe, and miſchiefe many others. From the <hi>heart come</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 15. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>euill thoughts, murthers, falſe teſtimonies, ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſaid he that knew the heart.</hi> But me thinkes I heare ſome whiſper; that thought is free: It is free indeede, but how? free from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection or puniſhment of man: but the <hi>Lord which made the frame of the heart and ſearcheth the thoughts, is a Iudge ſtanding before the doore</hi> therof, to <hi>condemne thoſe that doe but</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 5. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>grudge againſt their bretheren, ſaith ſaint Iames. Hell and deſtruction are before the Lord: how</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>much more the hearts of the ſonnes of men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſinne of the diuell was but an exaltation of the <hi>heart. A wicked heart is an abhomination to the Lord:</hi> although it want meanes, either of ſtrength to giue correſpondencie to the will, or audacitie to vtter the poyſon and ſpight in tearmes: for <hi>intention</hi> is <hi>action,</hi> and <hi>hating is</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>killing, before almightie God, the Iudge of all ſecrets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26599:15"/>
                  <p>The <hi>ſituation</hi> of <hi>Iericho</hi> was <hi>pleaſaunt,</hi> but the <hi>water was naught, and the ground vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and barren,</hi> till <hi>Eliſha</hi> the <hi>Prophet,</hi> by an<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>King. 2. 19.</hi>
                     </note> infuſion of <hi>Salt caſt into the ſpring of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, cured thoſe infectious qualities:</hi> and ſo <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued,</hi> is the eſtate of a profeſſed <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> pleaſaunt to behold with many ſeeming com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, which (if the waters of the <hi>heart</hi> be <hi>bitter</hi> and infectious with the inueterate <hi>leauen</hi> of <hi>malice</hi>) are all daſhed, and made matters of daunger and death, rather then meanes of comfort and life.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>ſalt</hi> which muſt be caſt into the <hi>Fountaine head</hi> of the <hi>hart,</hi> which beeing healed redreſſeth all daungers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences, and <hi>this</hi> is <hi>that word,</hi> and <hi>that ſalt</hi> wherewith wee deſire to ſeaſon and ſucke out all corrupt humors from the bottome of your hearts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auenge not your ſelues dearely beloued</hi> Diuerſe be the reaſons that backe this <hi>prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging hart.</note> and may make it of force to withdraw vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this priuate &amp; priuie rancour of the minde, though commonly the affections incenſed haue no <hi>eares.</hi> But ſee, (beloued) before the <hi>Cocatrice egges bee hatched,</hi> and they <hi>breake</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 59. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>out into a ſerpent,</hi> what trauaile, and payne, there is in the conception, &amp; breeding of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, &amp; nouriſhing of a reuenging <hi>thought.</hi> What diſeaſe can ſo diſfigure the <hi>bodie</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26599:15"/> conſume it? what loſſe can ſo take away the<note place="margin">Reuenge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> hart co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumes body, goods, and ſoule.</note> benefit of <hi>Riches or honour?</hi> or what canker can ſo infect and poyſon the <hi>ſoule,</hi> as an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious thirſt of <hi>vengeaunce,</hi> and a deſire to cry <hi>quittance</hi> with our enimies? Hee that carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">1. The bodie.</note> the fire of malice in his boſom, firſt burnes himſelfe, pyneth and ſcorcheth his braynes, dryeth the marrow of his boanes, drinketh vp his owne bloud, bewrayeth his worme-eaten conſcience with the malicious ſparkles of an euil eye. For as <hi>Wiſdome maketh the face to ſhine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 13. Prou. 14. 30.</note> 
                     <hi>and a ioyful hart maketh a cheerfull countenance,</hi> as a <hi>ſound minde is the life of the fleſh and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue to the boanes:</hi> ſo doth <hi>malice put the face</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 4. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>out of fauour, maketh Caine walke with hanging lookes, conſumeth the eyes</hi> in the holes, haſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth<note place="margin">Zechar. 14.</note> death to the body, &amp; <hi>filles the boanes with corruption.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſpirit of a man (ſayth Salomon) ſuſtayneth</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 18. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>his infirmitie: but a wounded ſpirit, who can bear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> it? Anger reſteth in the boſome of fooles, and yet</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> lyke a reſtleſſe beaſt it <hi>teareth the ſoule of him</hi> that keepeth it. It ſwelleth like poyſon, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4.</note> grin, and gnaſh the teeth like a dogge, for ſo it is ſaid of <hi>Stephens</hi> enemies, <hi>Their hearts burſt for ſpight, and they gnaſhed at him with</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 7. 54.</note> 
                     <hi>their teeth,</hi> they ſhew the tricks of hell, and the propertie of the diuell in this life, for <hi>Diaboli propria eſt inuidia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Baſil:</hi> Enuie of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Baſil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de Inui<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> ſinnes is the diuels peculiar brand, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26599:16"/> he is marked. Doe but take a view of the enuious creature, marke his ioy and laughter, it is but to ſee others weepe and wring: by this, haſtening vengeance vpon himſelfe, from the Lord which cauſeth malicious men to bee caught in their owne ſnares. Therefore (ſayth Salomon) <hi>be not</hi> glad, <hi>when thine enimie falleth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 24.</note> 
                     <hi>let not thine heart reioyce when he ſtumbleth, leaſt the Lord ſee it, and hee be diſpleaſed, and turne his wrath from him to thee.</hi> So great an enimie is the enuious man to himſelfe, that he deriues the plagues of others vpon his owne body and ſoule. Whereof <hi>Iob</hi> deſireth to cleare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">Iob. 31. 29.</note> proteſting that <hi>hee reioyced not at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of him that hated him, nor was moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to ioy, when euill came vpon him.</hi> As for the ſorrow and deadly vexation of the minde, which this deſire of reuenge, and hatred effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth,<note place="margin">2. The vſe of goods &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor abridged by reuenge of heart. <hi>Eſth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r. 5. 11.</hi>
                     </note> as it tormenteth the bodie, ſo it depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the rich of his eaſe, and the moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his contentment: his owne abundance cannot pleaſure him, nor his purple garments heale him. When <hi>Haman</hi> hath reconed vp <hi>all the glorie of his riches, the multitude of his children,</hi> all his promotions, wherwith the king had honored him, the fauour and banquet, wherewith the Queene had graced him, what is all this to cheere him vp that hath a clog in his heart, which driues him to confeſſe, <hi>that all this is nothing, ſo long as hee ſees Mordechat the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26599:16"/> Iew ſitting at the Kinges gate:</hi> ſo that <hi>Haman</hi> cannot <hi>goe ioyfully to the banquet,</hi> except he be the hangman of his enimie, for default of a little curteſie towards him. But if this venime were but only daungerous to the body, or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch as wrought a diſcontentment toward<note place="margin">3. Reuenge i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> heart an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſoule.</note> riches, honor, and things externall, it might ſeeme tolerable: but it poiſoneth alſo the ſoule, infecteth religion, intercepteth prayers, depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs of the ſight and preſence of the Lord.<note place="margin">1. Pet, 2. 11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All fleſhly luſtes</hi> (ſayth <hi>Peter) firſt fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſoule of our ſelues,</hi> and that before they harme the body of others; for hee that beareth fire in his boſome firſt burnes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, before hee endaunger his neighbours. Admit thou knoweſt the truth, canſt teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, frequent ſermons, profeſſe well, ſpeake fauourably, and Godly, yet if thou concealeſt a ſpightfull heart vnder this maſke of religion, thou art but as a <hi>potſheard ouerlaide with ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 26. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>droſſe,</hi> a <hi>guilded ſcpulchre,</hi> and all thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is but a lye, not able to affourd any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of conſcience to thyne owne ſoule: and therefore fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch hipocrites S. <hi>Iames</hi> pulleth of the vizard, and ſheweth them their owne eſtate.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If you haue bitter enuying and ſtrife in your</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 3. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>harts reioyce not, neither bee lyers againſt the truth.</hi> How can that minde which is ſtuffed with ſuperfluitie of malice, heare with profit
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26599:17"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:26599:17"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:26599:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:26599:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26599:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:26599:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:26599:20"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:26599:20"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:26599:21"/> that word, which is ſincere milke to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with meekeneſſe as of new borne babes?</p>
                  <p>Againe, what <hi>prayers</hi> can iſſue from a bitter fountaine? What deſire or delyght can the malicious heart haue to preſent it ſelfe before the Maieſtie of him that eſteemeth of <hi>hatred as manſlaughter?</hi> How dareſt thou offer thoſe ſighes and groanes to the Lord that breake fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a forge of reuenge? With what confidence canſt thou lift vp thoſe hands to God for mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that are readie to be lifted vp againſt thy brother in cruelty? ſeeing the Lord will haue <hi>pure hands lifted vp without wrath or doubting?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Timoth. 2. 8. Math. 5.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed are the pure in hart, for they ſhall ſee God: ſaith our ſauiour:</hi> their ſoule is a glaſſe of Gods cheerefull face: but <hi>hee that hateth his</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>brother is in darkneſſe.</hi> A turbulent ſpirit, and a ſpightfull heart is like a troubled water, wher there appeares no reflection of any comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble countenance, but dregges, terrour, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the ſhadow of death and crueltie, being the Image of the <hi>diuell</hi> himſelfe. For ther is no ſuch harbour for him to lurke and fortifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in, as that <hi>heart which is ſwept with anger,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 11. 21. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>and garniſhed with wrath:</hi> vpon whoſe <hi>rage the ſunne hath often ſet:</hi> therefore ſayth <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the <hi>Epheſ: Let not the ſunne goe downe vpon</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ephſe.</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6.</note> 
                     <hi>your wrath, giue no place to the dwell:</hi> Who if he get in league with the corrupted will, he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26599:21"/> imployeth not onely the heart, but the tongue, not onely the tongue, but <hi>the eyes alſo in witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Baſil.</note> 
                     <hi>and vilanie,</hi> being his worke commonly vpon a profound malice, and an inueterate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of reuenge. Seeing then the very thoughts of reuenge, are iudged and condemned of the Lord, ſeing they are the roote of all miſchiefes, the tormenters of the body, the diſfigurers of the face, the depriuers of reſt in the middeſt of riches &amp; honour; the ſlaughterers of the ſoule; the empeachment of religion; preiudiciall to the hearing, and hinderers of prayers, the eclipſe of the eye of our ſoule, that it cannot ſee God, nor be ſeene in peace of him; and the very har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bengers of the diuell, let vs that haue thought wickedly, (as who <hi>can ſay his heart is cleane?</hi>)<note place="margin">Prou. 20. 9.</note> lay our hands vpon our hearts, and yeeld our ſelues to the vertue of this <hi>prohibition, Auenge not your ſelues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As vpon the heart, ſo the holie ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth vs to lay our hands vpon the mouth, to ſtay the tongue, and ſurceaſe all practiſe of<note place="margin">2. The tong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſtayed from reuenge</note> reuenge, by any outward meanes: that if wee cannot rule our affections for loue of him that ſeeketh to bridle them, yet wee may tame our our tongue, and repreſſe our actions for feare of the magiſtrate, that is the <hi>miniſter of God to take</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>vengeaunce of all curſed ſpeakers,</hi> and wicked dooers. Two ſorts of people are concluded, and ſhut vp, within this reſtraint. One ſort are like
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26599:22"/> 
                     <hi>Lions,</hi> either roaring in high thundring words, or ramping in cruel maner vpon their pray. The other, like <hi>Foxes,</hi> cloſe, and ſubtill, but greedie notwithſtanding. One truſteth to his force: the other to his fraude: one taketh his luſt and libertie, ſcorning Gods ordinance, as a refuge for cowardes, and not a fitte redreſſe for them that haue nimble tongues of their owne, and <hi>hands ſwift to ſhed bloud.</hi> The other giues backe for aduauntage, and will crouch and bowe, till hee ſee his occaſion, and then hee is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, wee are by <hi>vertue</hi> of this <hi>warrant</hi> to charme thoſe great barkers, which vſing that womaniſh kinde of <hi>reuenge,</hi> doe bend their <hi>tongues like bowes, and ſhoote their words like ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</hi> If to call our <hi>brother Racha,</hi> as much to ſay, as paltrie felow, deſerueth the puniſhment<note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> of a councell, if the nicke-name of <hi>foole in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſed anger</hi> be worthie of <hi>hell fire;</hi> then what ſhall <hi>be giuen vnto thee thou falſe tongue, which</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 52. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>loueſt and vſeſt to ſpeake all wordes, that may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy? which cutteſt like a raſor, not onely thoſe</hi> that are preſent, but woundeſt, like <hi>a venemous</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 120. Barnard. de tripli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i cuſtod.</note> 
                     <hi>arrow,</hi> the abſent and vnſeene? <hi>Leuiter volat grauiter vulnerat,</hi> ſayth <hi>Bernard,</hi> of the ſpeach of a wicked tongue: it flies lightly, but pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth deepely: it entreth eaſily, but goes out hardly: and that more is, <hi>Vnoictu multos inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit,</hi> with one blowe it ſpoyles a multitude
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26599:22"/> How great is the <hi>wounde,</hi> that ſo ſmall a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon maketh? Saint <hi>Iames tearmeth it to bee</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iames 3.</note> 
                     <hi>a worlde of miſchiefe, a fire that enflameth the whole courſe of Nature, an vnrulie euill, full of deadly poyſon, a beaſt that no man can tame.</hi> And yet the <hi>Lordes bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ued</hi> are not to ſuffer this <hi>member</hi> runne riot in themſelues: for if<note place="margin">Iames 1. 26.</note> any man <hi>ſeeme religious, and refraineth not his tongue,</hi> but <hi>deceyueth his owne heart, this mans Religion is vaine.</hi> The <hi>beloned</hi> of the Lord that ſtriue to bee <hi>perfect,</hi> and to <hi>bridle the whole bodie,</hi> muſt not let the tongue looſe. Bleſsing and curſing, bitter water and ſweete, muſt not iſſue out of the fountaine of a ſanctified mouth. Nay, if a man reſpect but the benefites of a temporall eſtate, hee is to ſet <hi>a watch before his mouth. For if anie man long after life, and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3. 10. Pſal. 34.</note> 
                     <hi>to ſee good dayes, he muſt refraine his tongue from euill, and his lippes from guile, ſayth the holie Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ranke of thoſe, that practice this kind of <hi>Reuenge,</hi> there are ſome that would ſeeme to ſurceaſe from their bitter and vnlawfull courſe, but it is when they haue rather tired then tamed their tongues, &amp; ſpurged out their <hi>deadly poyſon</hi> to the ful, then they crie out, in the bitterneſſe of their <hi>heart,</hi> vpon God and the Magiſtrate for further <hi>vengeance</hi> againſt him, whom they haue moſt cruellie torne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praued alreadie.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:26599:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But they aſke and receaue not, for the ſpirit of</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>them luſteth after enuie:</hi> and their <hi>curſe being cauſeleſſe, flieth like a byrd, and ſettleth no where,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rou.</hi> 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>vnleſſe it returne to their owne boſome.</hi> S. <hi>Ierome,</hi> likeneth it vnto an <hi>arrow ſhot againſt a ſtone,</hi> which ſticketh not in the marke, but often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eronym: de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ta cleric.</note> 
                     <hi>Reſiliens percutit dirigentem: flying back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, it ſtriketh the Archer. As hee loued cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) ſo ſhall it come vnto him, it ſhall</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal. 109. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>come into his bowels like water, and like oyle into his boſome, it ſhall be as a garment to couer him, and a gyrdell to his loynes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Are all words of rebuke, and curſes the fruits of hatred, and actions of priuate reuenge, &amp; therfore vnlawfull? will ſome ſay: To which I anſwere, that there be reproofes of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> proceeding from loue, and curſes of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, iſſuing from zeale: and warranted by the ſpirit of God, and therefore are conſequent ſentences of his appointed wrath <hi>and vengeance</hi> vpon ſinners. <hi>Let the righteous reproue me ſaith</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 141. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Dauid, for that ſhall be as precious balme vpon my head. O fooles and ſlowe of heart,</hi> ſayd our <hi>Sauiour</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 24. 25.</note> to his <hi>diſciples: and, goe behinde mee Sathan,</hi> to<note place="margin">Math. 16. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>Peter,</hi> that a little before made a <hi>bleſſed confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of the truth. <hi>O fooliſh Galathians, who hath</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Galat. 3. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>bewitched you?</hi> writeth <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>thoſe for whom he trauayled twyce, that Chriſt might be formed in</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> In theſe reprehenſions, and taunting words was no malice but a zeale to gods truth, hatred
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26599:23"/> to ignorance, &amp; loue to the ſoules of the parties rebuked, and thence brake out theſe ſharp and charitable termes of reproofe. <hi>Habet vera Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citia</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Barnard. 24<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Epiſ.</note> 
                     <hi>obiurgationem interdum, adulationem nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Trew friendſhip chideth ſometimes, flattereth neuer.</hi> But the caſe ſeemeth harder in flat cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and prayers of execration, and vengeaunce, which notwithſtanding by warrant from the ſpirit of God, haue proceeded lawfully from the mouthes of holie men, in eſpeciall commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the ſame. What woes, and iudgements<note place="margin">Math. 11.</note> doth the Lord thunder out againſt Chorazim, and Bethſaida, againſt <hi>Phariſes, Scribes, and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 24. Ierem. 17. 18. Ierom. 18. 22</note> 
                     <hi>hypocrits? Ieremie,</hi> and <hi>Dauid praye moſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently</hi> againſt certaine enimies to <hi>God and them ſelues. Saint Paule</hi> in particular againſt <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>2. Timoth.</hi> 4. 14<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>the Copperſmith,</hi> prayeth the Lord, to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him according to his deedes,</hi> which were euill and cruell. <hi>Noah</hi> chaunged his fatherly<note place="margin">Geneſ. 9. 25.</note> words of bleſſing into a heauie curſe vpon his <hi>ſonne Cham,</hi> and his poſteritie.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall we ſay of all theſe, but that they were warranted by the ſpirit of God, and their place aſſigned to reprooue, and pronounce the ſharp ſentence of the Lord againſt his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſperate enimies reuealed vnto them. For the prayers<note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>guſt. in Pſa. 108.</note> and imprecations of thoſe that were in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>wed with a ſpirit of prophecie, came not from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſire or delight they had to ſee Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce vpon others for any priuate reſpect:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26599:24"/> no not that calling of <hi>fire</hi> from <hi>heauen,</hi> by <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. 2.</note> nor that deadlie <hi>curſe of Eliſha vpon the ill nurtured children:</hi> but <hi>Elias</hi> was fired with a peculiar ſpirit, againſt the enemies of God, which being doubled on his ſeruant, procured him in the Lordes name to curſe thoſe male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part boyes, that reproched the miniſterie of God, in the wanton mockerie of <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. So that thoſe curſes, whereupon preſent execution followed, were but <hi>modus praedicendi</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 108.</note> 
                     <hi>futura,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin, the maner of foretelling things to come:</hi> wherein the ſpirit giuing notice of Gods pleaſure, the Prophet pronounced the iuſt vengeance of God to enſue. If any one now vndertake to curſe, or call fire from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon any particular perſons, as the Pope banneth and curſeth the Lords annointed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie times: his <hi>praiers are turned into ſinne, hee</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 9. 55.</note> 
                     <hi>knoweth not what ſpirit he is of,</hi> and therefore where <hi>he curſeth, the Lord bleſſeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I heare (me thinkes) ſome one that hath caught a lewde cuſtome of ſwearing, curſing, and wiſhing vengeance at euerie worde, yet maketh this fooliſh excuſe for his filthie lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: Although I ſpeake all maner of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, curſe damnablie, ſweare horriblie, yet I proteſt (with a mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous oath) that I meane no harme, it is not for reuenge, or anger, but cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom: I am friends with God, and all the world; And thus hee would iuſtifie the tree when the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26599:24"/> fruits be wicked. He ſweares his yea and his nay backward and forward, hee ſalutes his friends, and ſeaſons his ieaſts with curſing &amp; banning: and ſhall we beleeue that he feares God, when he teares God on this maner? Shall wee thinke him ſo good a fellow, as he makes himſelfe? <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>the fauours of the wicked be crueltie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 12. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 14. 9.</note> his courteſies be curſings, his ſalutations ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and miſchiefe. <hi>Are not theſe ſuch fooles as make but a ſport of ſinne?</hi> Are not theſe ſuch deceitfull men, as feigne themſelues mad, and <hi>caſt firebrands at their friends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and then ſay: <hi>Am</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 26. 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>I not in ſport?</hi> It is the propertie of ſome dogs to barke not ſo much for curſtneſſe, as for cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,<note place="margin">Petrarch.</note> ſaith one: and yet it is but a curriſh qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie at the beſt: and ſurely hee that hath ſuch a continual iſſue, and canker in his mouth of rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten words, and bitter ſtreames, muſt needs haue a ſinke of corruption in the heart: and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſmall reconing hee maketh of curſing and blaſphemie, <hi>yet hee that ſweareth often, muſt needes bee like a ſeruant often beaten and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ecclus. 23. 10. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>bunched, which can not be without ſome ſcarre,</hi> ſaith the wiſe man: <hi>and if he knowledge not his ſinne, he maketh a double offenſe:</hi> for the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord, that wil demaund an <hi>account of euery</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 12. 36.</note> 
                     <hi>idle worde,</hi> will not <hi>hold him guiltleſſe</hi> vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly, that with monſtrous oathes taketh his name in vaine, howſoeuer the iudgements of the Lord are not regarded by the wicked.</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:26599:25"/>
                  <p>It is a queſtion moued, and anſwered by that learned father <hi>Baſil,</hi> whether he that vſeth au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious ſpeech, and raſh termes, and yet vpon admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſame, maketh anſwere, <hi>Nihil habeo mali in corde,</hi> I haue no euil in my heart,<note place="margin">Queſt. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iffuſ. expl.</note> be to be credited in this caſe or no; His an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is that it fareth with a ſicke ſoule, as with a ſicke body. The diſeaſes of the body appeare not to euery one; no not to the Patient him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, when he is in his ſharpeſt fittes: yet when he rageth &amp; ſpeaketh abſurdly and idly, though he ſaith hee is not ſicke, no man of meane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience will beleeue him, but rather pittie his caſe, being the more neere daunger, by how much hee ſeemes the farther from feeling and ſenſe of his griefe.</p>
                  <p>In which caſe an expert phyſicion acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the rules and ſignes of his art, is able to diſcerne the ſecret diſeaſe, and the daunger thereof, and better enforme the Patient of his eſtate, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtanders by, or the patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t afflicted himſelfe. So is it with a ſoule-ſicke wretch, that nether feels his corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor knows the depth of his deadly wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. For if he rage and belch out vnſauorie &amp; rotten words, curſings &amp; blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, though he ſay his hart is <hi>ſound and cleane,</hi> ſhall wee beleeue him? <hi>Nay rather let vs giue credit to the Lord, which as a moſt approued Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion hath</hi> ſet downe this <hi>Aphoriſme</hi> as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule: <hi>Malus homo &amp;c. An euill man out
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26599:25"/> of the euill treaſure of his hart bringeth forth euill.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 6. 45.</note> 
                     <hi>For</hi> of <hi>the aboundance of the heart the mouth ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</hi> And howſoeuer mans conſcience think it ſelfe cleare, or his mouth proteſteth of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie; yet God is <hi>greater then his conſcience,</hi> and will waken his ſleepie ſoule at the laſt, by the ſcourge of the ſame conſcience: but in the meane while wee are to know the tree by the fruict, and the fountaine by the water, aſſuring our ſelues, that where ſmoke and vapoures are there is ſome fire, and where maleuolent ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches breake forth, there is a malignant humour that ſets them a float.</p>
                  <p>The offenſe of an euill tongue increaſeth by circumſtances of the perſon, that is aſſaulted by the ryot of the ſame. The higheſt degree is to ſet the mouth againſt heauen, as <hi>Rabſache,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſa. 36.</note> and <hi>Iulian the Apoſtate did:</hi> the next is to <hi>curſe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10. 20. Exod. 22. 28.</note> 
                     <hi>the King,</hi> or <hi>ſpeake euill of the ruler of the people,</hi> to rayle at Authoritie: and then follow ſuch as vnnaturally <hi>curſe father or mother,</hi> or <hi>curſe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leuit. 20. 9.</note> their <hi>children</hi> as <hi>Michahs mother curſed hir ſon;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iudges. 17. 2. Leuit. 19. 14.</note> and ſuch as vncharitably curſe the deafe, which cannot heare, or fooliſhly curſe themſelues, and ſweare as <hi>Peter did,</hi> to get credit amongſt a<note place="margin">Mark. 14. 71.</note> curſed company that vſed belike that faſhion in their affirmations.</p>
                  <p>As in all theſe the impatiencie or corruption of a wicked hart is diſcouered, ſo alſo doth it ſhew it ſelfe in the rage and crueltie of a man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26599:26"/> againſt the verie dumbe cattell, the power of whoſe life and death is in his handes. <hi>Balaam</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um. 22. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>may diſcouer his wicked heart, when he exceedeth in wrath againſt his aſſe, and ſmiteth him with a ſtaffe, and wiſheth a ſword in his hand like a ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fian to kill him: for a good man is mercifull to his</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 12. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>cattell,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon:</hi> and the beaſt that hee may kill vpon an occaſion, hee will not curſe in his anger, for polluting his mouth, or inuring his tongue to a wicked cuſtome, for euill ſpeach corrupteth good maners. Nay <hi>Michael</hi> giueth vs an example, that we are not to blame no not the diuell himſelfe with curſed ſpeach, but to<note place="margin">Iude. 1. 9.</note> giue place to the Lord that ſhall rebuke him. And therefore they that defie him, and curſe him with outragious tearmes, rather ſerue him and pleaſe him, then offend him: for ſaith the wiſe man, <hi>When the vngodly man curſeth Satan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ecclus. 21. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>be curſeth his owne ſoule.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But of all other, no curſed ſpeakers are ſo daungerous in our eſtate, and neede ſo much to be curbed, as thoſe monſters which Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> ſhadoweth out in their colours, <hi>that walke after the fleſh, in the luſt of vncleanneſſe, deſpiſing gouernment, being preſumptuous, and ſtanding in their owne conceipt, and not fearing to ſpeake euill of thoſe that are in dignitie.</hi> Be there not many of that vipers brood, cockered vnder the Popes wings, that hiſſe like ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, at their dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt mother, and curſe like <hi>Shimei,</hi> caſting out
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26599:26"/> rayling bookes, like ſtones to hitte the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oyncted of the Lord? But they fall, like ſtones toſſed into the ayre, vpon their owne heades. Amongſt our ſelues at home: who is hee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that dares not reuile thoſe that are of greateſt vertue, beſt deſert, higheſt autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie? if they perceyue not ſuch to fauour their diſſolute behauiour. But when the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and drinke meete togither, as they doe in many of our licentious people now a dayes, then is euerie ſober man a noted enemie, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Magiſtrate that keepeth peace or good order, a profeſſed foe. The Drunkardes will<note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 12.</note> not ſticke to make ſonges of <hi>Dauid,</hi> nor ſpeake euill of the Gouernours; and it is like that if the wine fayled not, that is, their liuings melted not, and beggerie came not vppon them <hi>like an armed man,</hi> they woulde<note place="margin">Prou. 6. 11.</note> not bluſh to braue Authoritie in open place, and diſturbe the whole courſe of iuſtice. As for our ſelues that ſpeake of peace, wee are ſure to bee aſſayled with warre: when wee play vpon <hi>Dauids</hi> Harpe to eaſe their griefe, they caſt their ſpeares to wound vs: and charm wee neuer ſo ſweetlie, yet this Serpent of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge and malice, either is deafe and will not heare: or fierce and readie to ſting vs: but it is our portion: wee muſt beare it, you redreſſe it. And thus haue we diſcouered not only the humour, but the vapors and ſmoke of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26599:27"/> Reuenge kindled in the heart, and venting out at the mouth, that you the Lords beloued may ſee the deformitie, &amp; reforme the fault, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this <hi>prohibition of ſaint Pauls, Auenge not your ſelues:</hi> which hee expoundeth to the <hi>Epheſ. after this ſort: Let all buterneſſe, crying,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>euill ſpeaking, be put away with all maliciouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next after the tongue we arreſt by this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition<note place="margin">3. Reuenging ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds arreſted</note> the wilfull hands, and violent procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of thoſe that wil be their owne caruers, &amp; therfore without deliberation with themſelues, without expectation of Gods vengeaunce, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt right, reaſon, and al good order, reuenge their iniuries receiued in deede, or imagined in conceipt.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> heere ſpeaketh in tearmes of loue to all: but how ſhall wee ſpeake? or what ſtile ſhall we vſe to the rufflers, &amp; hackſters of our age? Shall wee call them beloued? That were out of faſhion with ſuch affectate male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, that take a pride to be partakers of the curſe of <hi>Iſmael:</hi> that <hi>had his hand vp againſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 16. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>man, and euery mans hand againſt him.</hi> Shall wee call them chriſtians, &amp; ſo teach them their dutie? That name fitteth not the tragicall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, and ſtage-like behauiour of our dayes: wherein euery <hi>Nouice,</hi> like a fury, learnes to cry <hi>Reuenge,</hi> to offer the ſtabbe, to threaten the piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll, and in their aduantage not to ſpare: no not a brother, but to ſtrike him, as <note n="*" place="margin">Primus diabo. li diſcipulus. Baſ. Geneſ. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Caine, the firſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26599:27"/> diſciple of the diuell, did Abel:</hi> not a reconciled friend, but to wound <hi>him traiterouſly</hi> as <hi>Ioab did</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 3. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>Abner.</hi> Alas how is that pretious accompt forgotten which the Lord maketh and deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of <hi>man and beaſt, for ſhedding of mans bloud,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 5.</note> with an vnpriuiledged ſword, and a priuate an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger! What ſmall reconing is made to deface the Image of God, or teare the fleſh of our ſelues, as though men were become wolues &amp; dragons, to their owne kinde! Is that valour &amp; fortitude ſo to feare another mans life, that thou canſt not liue in quiet, till thou haſt ſeene his death? Is it manhood, to be monſtrous, and cruell, like <hi>the ould Gyants;</hi> or <hi>ſauage, like beaſts of the pray?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If you prouoke beaſts, they lay about them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactant. lib. 6 Inſtit. Cap. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>with horne and hoofe, ſaith a father:</hi> and <hi>ſo doe fooles receiuing hurt, being led with a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonleſſe furie, to reuenge;</hi> they cannot reſpite theyr rage, nor mitigate theyr paſſions. <hi>A foole rageth and is careleſſe, and in the haſt of his anger hee committeth follie, ſayth that wiſe king:</hi> but<note place="margin">Prou. 14. 16.</note> ſhall the heate of his bloud excuſe his aſſaults of violence &amp; murder before the Lord? Shall his anger, being a ſhort madneſſe acquire him? Or ſhall the wounds that are giuen without<note place="margin">Prou. 23. 29.</note> cauſe, by ſuch as tarry long at the wine, till they are enraged with heate, and diſpoſſeſſed of wit, pleade a pardon for him, that killeth his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion in drinke? Aske but the Philoſopher,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:26599:28"/> and he will tell vs, <hi>that drunken offenſes deſerue double puniſhment,</hi> for ſuch madneſſe is volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie,<note place="margin">Ariſt. eth. 3.</note> and ſuch ignorance is wilfull: therefore our common ſpeach ſufficiently concludeth this poynt, which awardeth <hi>him that killeth a man when he is drunke, to bee hanged when hee is ſober.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But of all other, that ſame violence and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is effected by preſumption, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated circumſtances, is prohibited by the Lord, and to bee reſiſted by the ſworde of his vengeance. O that this ſinne might not bee found in the houſe of <hi>Iacob;</hi> But what age is this? Or what people doe wee liue amongſt? Bluntly to kill, and ſimplie to murther, is but for plaine fellowes: our gallants that ſtudie to bee madde with reaſon, haue an art of kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, rules, traditions, and precepts to teach them murther by the booke: in which they growe more expert then captaine <hi>Ioab,</hi> which<note place="margin">2. Sam. 3. 27. 2. Sam. 20. 10.</note> could take the <hi>firſt ribbe in his ſtabbes,</hi> where he was ſure to ſpeede. Such cunning there was in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> not long before the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation thereof: for common ſtabbers, with<note place="margin">Ioſeph. bell. Iud. lib. 2. cap. 12.</note> their cloaked poyniards, and ſhort daggers, in the middeſt of aſſemblies diſpatched thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt whome they made any quarrell, with<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>icarii.</note> great arte and ſecrecie. And it can bee no good preſagement in anie Countrie, when bloudthirſtie men growe expert, and boaſt like
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26599:28"/> tyrants, <hi>men of power and ſtrength</hi> to doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, and take away life: when alas <hi>it is more</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 52.</note> 
                     <hi>grace and proweſſe to giue life, or preſerue it: for euerie vermine, and baſe viper can wounde and kill: and is this a propertie for ſtrong men to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But wee heare dayly the replie of ſome in their impatient mood: What? <hi>ſhal we ſuffer all? be made fooles? accounted cowards?</hi> and be ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed, and bound to the peace, that euery one ſhal ouer-crow vs and oppreſſe vs? He that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp an old iniurie, prepares a new for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Theſe are to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that the ſame God which forbiddeth <hi>priuate reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge,</hi> hath ordained <hi>a publike redreſſe</hi> for all iniuries, either by them that carry the weapons of his wrath, or by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, if iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſlumber with them. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as we haue a reſtraint to keepe vs from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging<note place="margin">3. Direction.</note> our ſelues: ſo we haue a direction whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to go, &amp; ſpeed of a remedie in all our grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uances: <hi>Giue place vnto wrath.</hi> He that wil right his owne cauſe, &amp; be his own ſtickler &amp; cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion, takes the place of Gods wrath, &amp; intrudes himſelf; but the beloued of the Lord muſt giue place: if thou canſt not forbeare iniuries, yet forbeare, &amp; expect a day of hearing of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Iudge, or his lawful delegats. Neither whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priuate men ſee notorious ſinnes vnpuniſhed, is it lawfull for them vpon an ouerſhot zeale, to take vp the ſworde, and play the Reformers.</p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:26599:29"/>
                  <p>Such a one (wilt thou alledge) is a forſworne wretch, Gods enimie: and therefore I may doe the Lord good ſeruice to kill him.</p>
                  <p>Who art thou that ſo iudgeſt, and preſumeſt to haue powre of life and death, without a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion? Keepe thou thy bounds, wait vpon the Lord, tarrie his leaſure. Priuate me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue no further plea, but complaints to their ſuperiours, or teares and prayers to the Lord, in ſuch a caſe. <hi>Peter muſt put vp his ſword, or elſe Peter muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 26. 52.</note> 
                     <hi>with the ſword.</hi> Although <hi>Symeon and Leui,</hi> ſeeme to haue a iuſt cauſe of their violent courſe, againſt <hi>Shechem,</hi> and <hi>aſke if hee ſhould</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 34. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>abuſe their ſiſter, as an whore;</hi> yet theyr <hi>father layeth a brand of Gods wrath vpon them, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Geneſ. 49. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>brethren in euill, and ſlaying the man (though an offender) in their cruell rage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iudas and Theudas ſtarted vp in a time of tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and oppreſſion,</hi> when the people were mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly racked with the Romane exactions, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended<note place="margin">Actes. 5.</note> a deliuerance: but their enterpriſe, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not of God, came to naught, with all the parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</hi> The like ſucceſſe had the <hi>Anabaptiſts in Munſter,</hi> who made a religious ſhew, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing<note place="margin">Sleidan. lib. 5.</note> the tyrannie, and vngodlyneſſe of the gouernours of their times. And what other end had our <hi>Ket of Northfolke,</hi> or ſuch like vpſtarts? who ſwelling to a head by the confluence of many poore wretches, crying out reformation, at length burſt themſelues like a botch, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26599:29"/> declared their corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But we are otherwiſe<note place="margin">Prou. 24. 21.</note> taught, to feare God and the king, and not to meddle with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are ſeditious: to remoue our matters from our owne affection, to the Lords iudgement, not to <hi>auenge our ſelues, but giue place vnto his wrath:</hi> not that wee ſhould make the lawe (being his ordinance) an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to ſerue our luſts, as the foxes &amp; trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſuitors doe, of whom wee ſhall ſpeake heare after<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but that it may be a refuge to keepe vs in peace, to defend our innocencie, which if it doth not performe: yet patiently we are to expect the wrath of our God, that <hi>can ſtill the enemie and the Auenger</hi> in his good time. Now as many reaſons were raiſed from the louing title to keepe vs from reuenge, ſo is this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint<note place="margin">Foure reaſons againſt ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuenge. 1. Reaſon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the action of aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging.</note> full of matter to diſſwade from that ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter courſe.</p>
                  <p>If we conſider firſt this action of auenging, what is it but to repay euill with euill, to puniſh vice with ſinne, and to imitate the wicked in his workes and waies of miſchiefe? <hi>Qui malum</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactant. Improbitati oppoſita impatia en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ia magna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> concitat tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtates.</note> 
                     <hi>imitatur bonus eſſe non poteſt:</hi> he that imitateth the bad, cannot be good himſelfe. He ſhall <hi>haue as good as he brings,</hi> ſayeſt thou: he brings the fruite of iniuſtice, and thou payeſt him with the thornes of impatiencie. Becauſe thine enemie is vniuſt, wilt thou be vngodly? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is an oppreſſor, or a ſlaunderer, wilt thou be froward, and a murtherer? <hi>Ne vtaris
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26599:30"/> inimico praeceptore,</hi> ſaith <hi>Baſil:</hi> let not thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my be thy ſcholemaſter, to tech thee that which thou deteſteſt in him. Shuldeſt thou be a glaſſe to reſemble the fury &amp; madnes of the wicked in his angry moode? or ſhould thy voice be the Echo of his vngracious ſpeach? or thy hand the iuſtrument to bandy backe againe his balles of fire and miſchiefe? No, rather ouercome thee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill with good: fire quencheth not fire, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſettes all on a flame: neither can euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe euill, but increaſe it rather: and one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury linked to another (as <hi>Samſons</hi> foxes, faſtned with firebrands at their tailes) diſturbe the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, and deſtroy the fruit of whole ſocieties. But he that rendreth <hi>good for bad, heapeth hote coales vpon his enemies head,</hi> not to conſume him by his will, but to kindle and ſtir him to charitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, or at the leaſt to a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſuch as <hi>Saul</hi> made to <hi>Dauid; Thou art more righteous than I.</hi> This is the victory that<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Sam. 24. 18.</hi>
                     </note> Chriſtians, which are the heires of bleſſing, ſhould content themſelues withall. Contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,<note place="margin">Barnard admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lites templi.</note> 
                     <hi>Infelix victoriaeſt, in qua hominem ſupera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vitio ſuccu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bis:</hi> It is an vnglorious victory, when conquering a man, thou art foiled by a beaſtly vice.</p>
                  <p>Secondly if we note the perſon here diſcharged<note place="margin">2. Reaſons fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenging.</note> from <hi>reuenge:</hi> it is our ſelues. How abſurd it is that one man ſhould be plaintiffe, witneſſe, Iudge, and executioner, al himſelfe in his owne
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:26599:30"/> cauſe, the lawes of God, of men, of nature, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe can teach vs. <hi>He that is firſt in his</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prouerb. 18. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>owne cauſe is iuſt:</hi> that is: telleth a ſound tale for himſelfe, till his neighbour come and controll it. If the plaintiffe goe no further then the court of his owne affections, he ſhall haue all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour that may be, for he is <hi>Amicus curiae,</hi> and the defendant ſhall haue neither audience, nor aduocate there, but all extremitie: for what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing can be expected, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe, witneſſe, Iudge, and executioner all him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; but that the action ſhould be raſhly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced, the witneſſe corrupt, the iudgement partiall, and the execution both ſodaine and violent.</p>
                  <p>In regard whereof our priuate matters are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed from our owne partiall hearing, &amp; wee are inhibited as Iudges in competent to deale for our ſelues. And although Chriſtians ſhould cary a court of conſcience about them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there is no corruption, nor partiality, no hard meaſure intended to others, but ſuch as they deſire to be returned to themſelues, yet to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide the ſlander &amp; ſuſpition of iniuſtice, they are to abide the publike triall, &amp; to ſubmit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to the ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſure of the Lords appointed mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, &amp; in no caſe to defile their hands with the baſe execution of their owne reuenge.<note place="margin">3. From the direction, a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt reuenge.</note> A third reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is drawen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the direction made, to ſend vs where we ſhould ſeeke, &amp; may finde
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:26599:31"/> remedie of al enormities: <hi>Giue place vnto wrath.</hi> Wherin is thus much implyed, that although, thou haddeſt the ſword &amp; the law in thine own hand, and mighteſt be thine owne caruer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pion, yet thy hands might faile thy heart; though thy priuate anger be curſt, yet hath it but ſhort hornes: the ſtrongeſt reuenger mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth with his match. Therefore that auncient tryall by combat, is growne out of practiſe with Chriſtians, becauſe therein the innocent partie is as farre endaungered as the offender, the weake truth is made a prey to ſtrong falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, rather then a puniſhment: And the Lord hath ordained diligent inquiſition to ſift out offences, and an oath to be the end of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, and girded his magiſtrates with power and maieſty to ſuppreſſe the mightie, &amp; hath not left the defence of the innocent, or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge of the wicked, to one mans valour, or to the hazard of a thing vncertaine, or the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of a priuate mans wrath, which hath no warrant from the Lord, but is rather a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of God, then a due courſe of tryall in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters puniſhable by the ſword. It is not for the weakenes of mans anger to preuent the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of gods ordinance. <hi>Fret not thy ſelfe againſt ſinners to doe euill,</hi> but truſt in the Lord and hee will care for thee: be ſilent, and he will ſpeake for thee: ſtand thou ſtill, and he will fight in thy cauſe. If thou draweſt out thy wodden &amp;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26599:31"/> haſty dagger, he putteth his ſword into his ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berd, and leaues thee to thy ſelfe. A childe that is hurt, doth not turne againe, but runnes and complaines to his father: Chriſtians muſt as children, declare their wrongs to God their father, &amp; let him alone, <hi>giue place to his wrath:</hi> we are but vnderlings, he is our Champion: it is policie for the weake to giue ouer his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the ſtrong: it is duety to giue place to our betters, and danger to preoccupate &amp; take the Lords vengeance out of his ſtrong hand. Therefore let our hearts be ſtill, our tongues quiet, our hands peaceable, leaſt in priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge we imitate the wicked, ſhew our ſelues corrupt Iudges, baſe executioners, preuent the Lords aſſiſtance, and periſh in our owne weake and froward waies.</p>
                  <p>But I neede not ſtand longer to preſſe the wordes of the <hi>prohibition,</hi> for arguments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this <hi>priuate reuenge:</hi> ſeeing we may ſhew a tranſcript and copie, out of gods ſacred char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and holy Oracles to take down the hearts, ſilence the mouthes, and reſtraine the handes<note place="margin">2. Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> of all ſleſh, from their ſiniſter proceedings. What art thou that dareſt intrude into gods right and title? Vengeance is mine; what art thou that threatneſt, and ſayeſt thou wilt do to thy foe, as he hath done to thee? I will repay, ſaith the Lord. As in the <hi>prohibition</hi> the ſword of vengeance is wreſted out of euery priuate
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:26599:32"/> mans hand, and they brought to attend the Lords power and pleaſure for the righting of their wrongs: ſo in this confirmation, the Lord as it were <hi>cloathed in his royall apparel, his crowne of maieſty vpon his head, the earth trembling at</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 93. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>his lookes, deuouring fire going from his throne,</hi> maketh knowne his title by this claime, <hi>venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is mine:</hi> and taking his ſword, ſeemeth to ſhake and brandiſh it in threatning manner, againſt all vſurpers, &amp; euill doers: with this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition: <hi>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance is mine, I will repay:</hi> ſaith the Lord. Behold (Right worſhipful) the Patent &amp; charter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence your authority is deriued, &amp; whereby the reuerence and ſubmiſſion that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſoule muſt yeelde, is procured and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced. All creatures and ordinances be the Lords, but this ordinance of iudgement he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titleth himſelfe vnto, by preciſe, and ſpeciall tearmes, as being a thing wherin he will migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily declare his power and maieſty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">1 The cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge bp the exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ution. 3. The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ption.</note> firſt is recorded his challenge: <hi>vengeance is mine:</hi> ſecondly his execution of the ſame, <hi>I will repay it:</hi> thirdly the ſubſcription of his great name is affixed, as thus: ſaith the Lord. That this is the Lords true act and deede, and a faithfull copie out of the Originall, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the Regiſter of Gods holy ſpirit giueth witneſſe, with <hi>ſcriptum eſt:</hi> it is written. The diuell beganne with the like floriſh of <hi>ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt,</hi> twiſe when hee tempted Chriſt, to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26599:32"/> make <hi>ſtones of bread,</hi> and to caſt himſelfe from a pinnacle: yet hee brought but a ſhadowe no ſubſtance, he vrged the letter but not the trew meaning: but when he came to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world and the glory thereof, he<note place="margin">Luke. 4. 6.</note> fled from his ſcripture, and hath not ſo much as one letter or tittle to plead, but onely his bare worde, <hi>All theſe are mine;</hi> If you aſke how he came by them, he anſweres as the theefe at the barre, they were deliuered vnto him, by whom he cannot tell, the time he remembers not, the place he hath forgot: which is as much to ſay, they are none of his indeede, hee holdes them by vſurpation, not by any right, hee forgeth a donation, but can make no deliuery nor good warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize of his gifts. But the Lord, which is witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be the ſame which <hi>raigned of olde,</hi> which <hi>made all nations, and therefore correcteth all,</hi> did<note place="margin">Pſal. 55. 19. 94. 10. Deut. 32. 35.</note> thunder out his glorious chalenge by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and confirmed by wonders and miracles, that vengeance and recompenſe was his;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that <hi>Dauid</hi> giues teſtimonie, of the Lords title againe and againe repeated in<note place="margin">Pſal. 62. 11.</note> his hearing: <hi>GOD spake once and twice, I haue heard it, that power belongeth vnto GOD.</hi> And the Apoſtle in this place, ſheweth the Lords former title, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the continuance of poſſeſſion without interruption: For it is wtitten, ſaith hee,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26599:33"/> and the ſcripture is not in vaine which ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth after this maner, <hi>vengeance is mine, I will repay,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
                  <p>This vengeance ſo claimed by the Lord, is<note place="margin">Vengeance ſpiritual<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> eyther ſpirituall, or ciuill and corporall. The ſpirituall vengeance is not aſſigned to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of God, in pompe, &amp; externall violence; <hi>For the weapons of our warrefare be not carnall</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 10 4.</note> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) but mighty through God;</hi> the beautie is not outward, but within: the power is not to tyrannize vpon the bodie by a ſecular arme, nor yet to ſley the ſoule, as the man of ſinne would ſeeme with his brutiſh thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolts, but to threaten from God, to declare &amp; pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the vengeance of the Lord, but leaue the execution to himſelfe, becauſe we know he will repay, and to this effect, the Author to the<note place="margin">Heb. 10 30.</note> 
                     <hi>Hebrewes</hi> produceth this ſame charter, as one that ſpeaketh by knowledge: <hi>we know him that hath ſaide: vengeance is mine I will recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe,</hi> ſaith the Lord.<note place="margin">Vengeance temporall.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>That vengeance which is corporall &amp; reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth but the bodie, is partly reſerued to the lords owne hand, immediatly to inflict particularly in this life, and generally, at the laſt great day of his vengeance: partly it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes, and his miniſters of wrath to cheriſhe the well doers, and cut downe the euill. So that though it pleaſe him to call his Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vengeance, and to claime it; by this moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26599:33"/> denomination to ſtrike feare and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence into all mens hearts: yet by the ſame ſpeach he vnderſtandeth alſo that mercy and fauour belongeth to him: as it doth indeed more properly &amp; naturally. For ſaith <hi>Barnard,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Inſerm. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at. Domi.</note> he is called not only the God of vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but <hi>pater m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ricordiarum,</hi> the father of mercies: <hi>becauſe out of himſelfe, and the bowels of his owne natiue goodneſſe, he takes matter of compaſſion, and mercy: ſed quòd Iudicat &amp; condemnit, nos e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um quodammodo cogimus:</hi> but in that he iudgeth<note place="margin">In vengeance there muſt be mercy.</note> and condemneth, the matter and occaſion is in our ſelues, and we after a ſort compell him vnto it. We haue therefore the example &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Lord himſelfe, to keepe vs that are priuate, from intruſion, diſobedience, or a hard conceipt of the magiſtrate, ſuch as the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> are poſſeſſed with, affirming the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique gouern our to be a neceſſarie euill, and<note place="margin">Danaeus. de ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. 4. cap. 24.</note> rather a plague, then a benefit to Chriſtians, becauſe he doth puniſh. And the ſame example from the Lord we may ſhewe as a preſident, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe rulers that be all for vengeance, and extremitie; nothing for mercy nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion. For the Lord hath appointed the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to be ſhepheards and watchmen, to feed and preſerue: not <hi>roaring lyons</hi> and <hi>hungry beares</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pro 28. 15. Micha. 3.</note> to prey vpon <hi>the people, to trample vpon them as mire, and grinde them in peeces with extortion &amp; polling.</hi> Our Sauiour Chriſt therefore calleth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26599:34"/> gouernors <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, benefactors and gracious, not malefactors and miſchieuous, becauſe by their title hee would teach them their duety. And if the Lord had ordained his magiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates onely to kill, to racke, and to poll his people, hee might haue put in the diuell for a ſole Commiſſioner, for hee can practiſe nothing elſe, but miſchiefe and vengeance: but becauſe the magiſtrate muſt vſe mercie and a fauourable defence of the good, a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of euill, and not a confuſion of all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: therefore hath the Lord committed his ſword vnto men, and gaue them this title, <hi>I haue ſaide you are Gods,</hi> intending they ſhould<note place="margin">Pſal. 82. 6.</note> be iuſt as God, holy as God, mercifull vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion as God, without partiality as God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iniquity as God, &amp; ſo doing, they may be feareleſſe of the faces of men, as God himſelfe. Thus may all men in authoritie behold their faces &amp; dueties in the glaſſe which ſheweth the Lords properties, and telleth them how neere they come to his perfection. The Lord doth not onely exerciſe puniſhment, but pitie, and compaſſion. How farre be thoſe Iudges and officers from the Lords example, that pinch all in the purſe, let none goe free, what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſoeuer in what cauſe ſoeuer, if hee light in their clawes, whoſe courts reſemble the <hi>Popes Purgatory;</hi> if he ſay the word, or any of his proctors, that the ſoules of men are in,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:26599:34"/> though they be out, yet pay they muſt by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues or their friendes, before they be at reſt, though they were at quiet before. And how like are ſuch to the ignorant phyſitions, that preſcribe to all perſons, in all cauſes, phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomie and letting of bloud, as though euery diſeaſe were of exceſſe and ſuperfluitie, none of defect and penurie: for they drawe bloud of all, and lighten the purſe of euery Patient, and this maketh the world to decreaſe in wealth, but increaſe in ſinnes. What warrant ſuch offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers haue for their dealings, I knowe not, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be this vulgar proued trewe: <hi>hee that buyes deare, muſt ſeldeare,</hi> &amp; he that farmes at a hard rent, <hi>muſt take vp all with the angle, &amp; drag all with the net.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neuertheleſſe it is a more deſperate caſe, when in a Commonwealth a man may do any thing without puniſhment, then when hee can doe nothing, but he ſmarts for it. A licentious liberty is more da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous then ſeruitude it ſelfe: &amp; therfore better haue a ſharpe gouernour, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <note place="margin">In execution mercy, but not remiſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> 
                     <hi>an Idole &amp; a blocke,</hi> that ſuffereth the people to be deuoured one of another, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Wherfore as the Lord conueyeth ouer his authority to men, &amp; confirmeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their place, with theſe titles, that <hi>Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is his; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is his; the throne his; the ſword his; &amp; vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is his:</hi> ſo he teacheth them the diligent vſe, &amp; carefull execution, adding this clauſe, <hi>I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay.</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:26599:35"/> When <hi>Iehos hap hat</hi> had ordained Iudges vnder him, he giueth them the ſame charge, that he had receiued from God &amp; the ſame en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement. <hi>Take beede what yee do: for ye ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute not the Iudgements of man, but of the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Chron. 19. 6</note> 
                     <hi>and hee will be with you in the cauſe of iudgement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wherefore now let the feare of the Lord be vpon you: take heede, and doe it: for there is no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie with the Lord our God, neither respect of perſon, nor receiuing of rewarde.</hi> So that the place of a Iudge is not a place of priuate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, nor a dumbe ſhewe of honour and pompe: nor a pillowe of eaſe and ſecuritie whereon men are to ſleepe, or tell the clocke: but there muſt be circumſpection, diligence and wiſdome: they muſt take heede, and doe it, <hi>hoc agite,</hi> attend vpon this office: doe this, and yet take heede what ye doe. When the Lord hath ſaide to rulers, <hi>yee are gods,</hi> hee meaneth not that they ſhoulde be like the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures idle god,</hi> which ſate in his throne, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> let all inferior matters alone, as to baſe for his eyes: nay rather the Lord woulde haue them like himſelfe, which doth not onely<note place="margin">Iſai. 40. 12.</note> weigh <hi>mountaines and hilles in his ballance, but the very duſt of the earth, and ſandes of the ſea.</hi> And therefore he ſetteth downe iudgement<note place="margin">Exod. 18. 22.</note> for ſmall matters: and as he ſaith <hi>vengeance is mine,</hi> ſo by <hi>Salomon</hi> he deſcendeth lower, and<note place="margin">Prou. 16. 11.</note> layeth claime to the <hi>ballance,</hi> and telleth vs
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:26599:35"/> that <hi>all the weightes in the bagge, be the worke of the Lord.</hi> And who are weaker or lower, then the fatherleſſe, the widowe, the poore? and yet al Iudges haue the Lords Letter <hi>commendatory,</hi> or <hi>mandatory</hi> rather, in their behalfe: the tenor whereof is this; <hi>doe right to the poore and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> 
                     <hi>doe Iuſtice to the poore and needy:</hi> and how they ſhould do this right, he telleth them: <hi>deliuer the poore and needy: ſaue them from the hand of the wicked.</hi> And further to keepe the Iudges themſelues in awe, hee ſtandeth ouer them, and telleth them of his preſence, in the very entrance of the Pſalme, ſaying: <hi>God ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the aſſembly of gods, hee Iudgeth amongſt gods:</hi> he maketh one, in all <hi>courts,</hi> all <hi>aſſiſes,</hi> &amp;<note place="margin">Pſal. 82. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeſſions,</hi> and that which men paſſe ouer, he finds out: that which they winke at, hee puniſheth. The Iudges ignorance will not excuſe him, if for careleſnes, he ſuffer the calamitie of the innocent: for if thou ſay, <hi>Behold we knew not of it;</hi> the <hi>holy Ghoſt will reply as in the Prouerbes, hee that po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dereth the heart, doth not he vnderſtand it?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 24. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>and hee that keepeth thy ſoule, knoweth hee it not? and will not hee alſo recompenſe euery man according to his worke?</hi> And the righteous man <hi>Iob</hi> will teach thee in dignitie, what thou oughteſt to haue done, in his Apology, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching<note place="margin">Iob. 29. 16.</note> intricate matters, for <hi>when he knewe not the cauſe, hee ſought it out diligently,</hi> as hee ſaith of himſelfe. At leaſtwiſe the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:26599:36"/> that vpon the clamorous outcry of <hi>Sodomes</hi> ſinnes in his eares, commeth downe<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. 18. 21.</note> on the earth, to examine if their ſinnes were ſo grieuous or no: doth rather intend an inſtruction to thoſe whom he honoureth with the title of Gods: then further intelligence to his owne wiſdome, from the which nothing was hidde.</p>
                  <p>According to the power aſſigned from God, muſt be the purpoſe, &amp; practiſe of euery gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. For what is a ſword, if it be alwaies like a childes dagger, riuetted in the ſheath, and put to no vſe? what are good lawes without execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but as belles without clappers? And what are magiſtrates, that hauing neither the life nor ſoule of iuſtice in themſelues, &amp; therefore cannot quicken the dead letter of the lawes, nor make them effectuall in ſound or motion? Are not they rather Idoles tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods? rather I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages that muſt be kept by a ſexten &amp; keeper<note place="margin">Lodouic. Viues in. 1. lib. cap. 3. de ciuit. Dei.</note> (for ſo <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaketh of voluptuous and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting gouernours) then guardians and keepers of cuntryes, cityes and people themſelues?</p>
                  <p>It is a trewe ſaying experimented daily, that <hi>Magiſtratus indicat virum: the honour and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aristot. lib. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>of an office, maketh triall what is in the man that beares it.</hi> A priuate man like an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty veſſell may haue many flawes and crackes, many faults and defectes that appeare not: but as when veſſelles are filled, the chinkes are
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:26599:36"/> deſcryed, by the leakeage of the wine: ſo when men are graced with authoritie, their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundneſſe is diſcouered through ſome chinke of folly, or feare, or careleſneſſe, or elſe they proue ſtaunche, and ſhewe their ſufficiency, for wiſdome and conſcience.</p>
                  <p>The beſt courſe in thoſe that haue a prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence to ordaine officers, is to try them by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, firſt if they wil be faithfull in little things, that ſo they may be credited at laſt with the great: or as men proue their veſſelles, with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, before they truſt them with wine. <hi>Abſolon</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> will be lowly &amp; popular to al ſuiters, &amp; promiſe faire to doe Iuſtice, till he get aloft, and then he ſheweth himſelfe neither to feare God nor the king, neither to care for Iuſtice nor honeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Men can ſpreade the nets of humilitie, and weaue them with the knots of ſubtiltie, till they haue caught their deſire, and then they ſhewe their hypocriſie. <hi>It ſeemeth that Pope Boniface followed this courſe in his clym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> of whome it is ſpoken<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Intrauit vt vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Faſcic<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> temp. Boniface. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>regnauit vt leo, mortuus vt canis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> hee entered like a foxe, hee ruled like a lyon, hee dyed like a dogge. And ſo commonly it comes to paſſe, a badde beginning hath a wicked proceeding, and a miſerable ende. Wherefore it is expedient for men of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, worſhippe, and authoritie to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie this title of the Lorde, and this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:26599:37"/> of execution in their memorie, that by it they may be comforted in their good procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, repreſſed from cruelty, &amp; the exerciſe of priuate reuenge in their publike actions; &amp; yet ſtirred vp to be diligent &amp; carefull, becauſe the Lord himſelfe is not only a looker on, but a chiefe Actor. <hi>For vengeance is mine, and I will repay,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
                  <p>Now ſhall it be requiſite againe to returne to priuate men, and the people of God for whoſe ſake the Lord hath vouchſafed his power and maieſty, his iuſtice and equitie, to be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and executed by worthy men ordained for that end. They are inhibited fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that reuenge, which they could not execute without ſinne: &amp; ſent vnto the courts of gods Iudgement, where they may haue a defence of innocencie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repulſe. If any ſhall obiect the faults, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes, and circumuentions of courts and lawes, thereby colouring their diſobedience to ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior powers, they muſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce muſt not be reſiſted for the perſonal crimes &amp; defects of thoſe that ſupply the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but rather be obeyed, becauſe the ſparkes of gods maieſty &amp; iuſtice remaine in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure in euery magiſtrate. The image &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a Prince, ſtamped in baſemetall, is currant amongſt his ſubiects, as well as that which is made in the fineſt ſiluer, though in deed it be not ſo pretious. S. <hi>Peter</hi> admoniſheth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:26599:37"/> ſeruants, and vnder that title, ſubiects, to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient in all feare, not onely <hi>to the good and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. 2. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>courteous,</hi> but alſo to the <hi>froward.</hi> There be two ſorts of people that abuſe themſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſacred ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of lawes, magiſtrates, and gouernours; appointed notwithſtanding for the puniſhment of euill, and the deciſion of controuerſies, that Gods people might liue in honeſtie and peace.</p>
                  <p>The one ſort are flat Recuſants, as Libertines,<note place="margin">1. Recuſants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ciuill ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</note> and Anabaptiſts: and ſuch tumultuous fellowes as would haue al ſubiect to their luſts, but they will be ſubiect to no lawes.</p>
                  <p>The other are Foxes that make accompt of<note place="margin">2. Foxes and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> abuſers of the lawes.</note> the Iudges and lawes, and vſe them to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of their priuate reuenge, and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humours.</p>
                  <p>Somewhat are we to ſpeake, God willing, of both: and firſt, of thoſe former Recuſants? not becauſe any ſuch are in this place: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe vnquiet, and troubleſome ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ters, that follow the lawe to ſerue their luſts: when they faile of their hope, for the moſt part turne from one extreame to another, and ſet themſelues cleane at defiance, with Iuſtice &amp; Authoritie.</p>
                  <p>Touching Libertines, which <hi>promiſe others li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Recuſants Libertimes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 19.</hi>
                     </note> themſelues being the <hi>ſeruants of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which walke after their luſts, and deſpiſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment,</hi> it is no maruell if they ſcorne and contemne order and magiſtracie, ſeeing they
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:26599:38"/> dare open their mouthes againſt heauen, and ſay, <hi>There is no God.</hi> But as they bluſh not to be called the <hi>Damned crew:</hi> thereby ſentencing themſelues, to confuſion; So Saint <hi>Peter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compteth</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Pet. 2. 12.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>them as bruit beaſtes, led with ſenſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and made to be taken and deſtroyed.</hi> If you aske howe they ſhall periſh? Saint <hi>Peter</hi> anſwereth, through their owne corruption, the cordes of their owne ſinne ſhall ſtoppe their breath: and though they eſcape long, and ſhift often; <hi>yet the Lord knoweth how to reſerue</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Pet. 2. 9.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>them to the day of vengeance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Anabaptiſts, and ſuch as leane to their<note place="margin">Recuſant Anabaptiſts.</note> ſtubborne conceipt, are alſo within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of ſuch Recuſants. They would haue all things co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to their owne luſts, and nothing reſerued or kept for any mans need. Becauſe ſome rulers are wicked, therfore they will haue no rule nor gouernment at al to be ouer them: a gratefull principle to them that deſire to be lawleſſe. I know the good father <hi>Tertullian</hi> may be produced as a patrone for theeſe: for hee<note place="margin">Dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. de hereſ. cap. 86.</note> was ouertaken by this errour, that he thought the <hi>vſe of the ſworde in battell, or puniſhments coulde not bee lawfull, and therefore degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all capitall and criminall Iudges from their places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But fathers as men might be deceiued, and ſo was <hi>Tertullian:</hi> the Lord himſelfe can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceiue, nor bee deceiued, and hee hath
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:26599:38"/> ſaid, <hi>Vengeaunce is mine.</hi> He hath ſaid, <hi>Giue</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 22. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>vnto Caeſar, that which is Caeſars.</hi> Hee by his worde hath created the Magiſtrate, called him his <hi>Miniſter,</hi> put <hi>the ſword in his hand, charged</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>him to ſtrike:</hi> and commaunded <hi>euerie ſoule to be ſubiect, not ſo much for feare, as the wicked are,</hi> but euen for conſcience, as the godly. He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>the captiues by Ieremie, to ſeeke the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ierem.</hi> 29. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>of Babylon, and pray vnto the Lord for it: He exhorted by Paule, that inteceſſions and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1. Tim.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>ſupplications ſhould be</hi> made for Kings and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all that were in authoritie: the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> knew not God, the rulers in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time were no Chriſtians, but heathens and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants: yet ſuch gouernours are to bee obeyed, and prayed for: that vnder them Chriſtians may liue in peace, godlines, and honeſty: how much more the faithful gouernors, that ſeeke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the peace of <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; the righteouſnes of Gods kingdome? though many blemiſhes may be noted, and imperfections of men, in the adminiſtration of iudgement vnder them.</p>
                  <p>Here may we not forget the Papiſtical Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie,<note place="margin">Recuſant Papiſts.</note> that acknowledge the power of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they would haue their peſtilen tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred executed againſt the ſaints of God, which they call heretikes: but when iuſtice ſhoulde worthilye bee turned vpon themſelues, then they pleade exemptions, and priuiledges, they are ſpirituall &amp; may not be touched; forgetting
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:26599:39"/> that which the Lord hath ſet downe for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Canon: <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect.</hi> Which <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> expoundeth of Church-men, as well as of lay people: <hi>Siue Apoſtolus, ſiue Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſta, ſiue Propheta fueris, Magiſtratui ſubeſſe debes.</hi> Be thou Apoſtle, Euangeliſt, or Prophet, or whatſoeuer, thou muſt yeeld ſubiection to the temporall Magiſtrate.</p>
                  <p>As theſe would exempt themſelues from their due obedience to Rulers; and yet ſhrowd themſelues vnder their wings, for reuenge, or defence: ſo <hi>Iulian the Apoſtate,</hi> did exact obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and tribute, belonging to gouernours: but perſwaded all Chriſtians, that his tyrannie and crueltie, was good for them, <hi>they might not reſiſt but ſuffer:</hi> If hee ſtroke them vpon one cheeke, <hi>they ſhould turne the other:</hi> thus, in an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious ieaſt, ſending in deede his ſubiects to heauen, and himſelfe merrily into hell. It ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, the common tranſlation, which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts follow, ſpeaketh contrarie to their own practiſe and meaning: <hi>Non defendentes,</hi> hath the tranſlation in this place; not defending your ſelues: but their practiſe is contrarie: for they trouble heauen and earth, for the auenging of their quarrelles: and doubt not by any violent proceedings to ſupplant Kings and Princes, and depoſe them from their thrones, being ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and warranted by that helliſh reſolution of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeauenth, &amp; his ſucceſſors: that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:26599:39"/> treaſon againſt vnbeleeuing Princes is lawfull.</p>
                  <p>But touching the wordes of our Sauiour Chriſt, where he prepareth Chriſtians to beare iniuries without reſiſtance: they take not away publike and lawfull defence, ſuch as is ſought by a due courſe of complaint, or reply, at the hand of the Magiſtrate, without rancour and heart-burning. For when he teacheth Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that being <hi>ſmitten vpon one cheeke, they</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhould turne, to him that ſmiteth, the other:</hi> he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth they ſhould bee ſo farre from rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one blowe for another, that rather they ſhould ſuffer two, then reuenge one: <hi>and yet not to faile in the lawfull defence of themſelues.</hi> For in the ſame Chapter immediately, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſaith: <hi>Agree with thine aduerſarie quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leaſt he deliuer thee to the Iudge, and the Iudge to the Sergeant;</hi> without doubt ratifying the courſe of ciuill proceedings in iudgement. Moreouer, he giueth example of this himſelfe, who being ſmitten, did not ſtrike againe, but yet he expoſtulateth <hi>de facto, touching the deed,</hi> whether it were lawfull or no, in him that ſtrook him. <hi>If I haue euill ſpoken, beare witneſſe of the euill: but if I haue well ſpoken, why ſmiteſt</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 18. 23. Auguſt. ad Marcellin.</note> 
                     <hi>thou me? Vbi oſtendit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſten) praepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem maxillae faciendam eſſe in corde:</hi> where he ſheweth that the preparation of the other cheeke muſt be made in the heart. For ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 56.</note> 
                     <hi>Ieſus gaue his cheekes to the nippers,</hi> and was not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26599:40"/> onely content to <hi>ſuffer blowes, but death for his enimies.</hi> The like example giueth <hi>Paule</hi> before the high prieſt, reprouing the iniuſtice of the<note place="margin">Acts. 23. 3. Acts. 21. 13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>om. 9. 3. Acts. 23. 17.</note> Iudge, and yet prepared <hi>to ſuffer bondes and death,</hi> and <hi>to bee ſeparate from Chriſt for his countrimen.</hi> Moreouer, did not the ſame <hi>Paul</hi> obtaine a ſafe conduct for his ſafegard, againſt certaine wretched fellowes that had ſworne his death? Did he not appeale to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and<note place="margin">Acts. 25. 12.</note> take the honeſt aduauntages of the lawe to helpe himſelfe? If this were the practiſe of the beſt men, who doubteth but our Sauiours precept reſpecteth the heart, and priuate court of mans conſcience, prouiding againſt all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiencie, and immoderate deſire of reuenge, but leauing open the lawe for a lawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and open preſeruation of life, goods, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and name. <hi>So then the law is good, if it be not abuſed,</hi> as it is ſaide in another ſenſe: for it ſerueth to redreſſe all wrongs, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe all tumults, and therefore was it a wiſe ſpeach of the towne Clerke of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to the raging Idolaters: <hi>If Demetrius, or the crafts me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue a matter againſt any man, the law is open, and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts. 19. 38.</note> 
                     <hi>there are deputies, let them accuſe one another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And here come in the foxes and followers of<note place="margin">Such as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe the law by oueruſing the ſame.</note> the law, ſuch as will not reuenge in words, nor blowes, but rather deſire to bee ſlaundered, and to take blowes, yet not for any meekneſſe, but to get an aduauntage in lawe, wherein
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26599:40"/> they may ſhew all extremitie of lingering re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge. And here they ſpend their witte, their wealth, their friends, their time, their ſoules, &amp; all: as the Spider that woorketh out her owne bowels, to compaſſe hir prey. Wil you examine what be their actions and ſuits co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly words of vnkindneſſe, actions of ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſlaunder, ſome treſpaſſe <hi>pedibus ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lando: de lanacaprina, &amp; aſini vmbra.</hi> Of goates wooll, and the ſhadow of an aſſe. How do theſe Sycophants abuſe the ordinance of God, with their contention for trifles? They are not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like thoſe nice people, that continually lie in the handes of phyſitions and ſurgeons for pimples and warts, when both the phyſition and the lawyer was appointed for neceſſity, and not for wantonneſſe. Am I deceiued? or do I not ſee theſe ſuters peſtered with boxes and papers (the bookes of their profeſſion) to courſe about from place to place, more buſie to caſt away their money then then the lawyer to catch it: They haue a running ſore of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, and malice, but their worde is onely <hi>Currat lex,</hi> Let the lawe haue his courſe: a courſe they meane without ende, except they can ſaciate their wilfull mindes with a full triumph ouer their impoueriſhed aduerſarie. Their courage is inuincible: for neither the admonition of friendes, threates of authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, no nor badde ſucceſſe in theyr ſuytes,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:26599:41"/> can make them giue ouer, and ſit downe by it: for it fares with them as with the drunkard in the <hi>Prouerbes,</hi> that boaſteth after this maner: <hi>They haue ſtricken me, but I was not ſicke: they</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 23. 35.</note> 
                     <hi>haue beaten me, but I knewe not of it, when I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woke: therefore will I ſeeke it yet ſtill.</hi> As ſuch ſeeke the wine when it hath bitten them, ſo theſe being drunken in the purſuite of their malice, though they ſmarted a while, and caught an ouerthrowe, yet will rouze them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and to it againe: for hote gamſters will take no checke, nor repulſe: loſing is no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; but the more they loſe, the more they ſeeke to venture.</p>
                  <p>I know what this generation will replie, if they heare me: <hi>We haue ſtoode before the beſt in good preſence, in the higheſt Courtes of greateſt honour, and iuſtice.</hi> Surely I graunt it, for the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der worketh <hi>hir webbes, and taketh holde with</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 30. 28.</note> 
                     <hi>hir handes, often in Kings palaces; and Satan, the father of all falſe accuſers, liers, and buſie bodies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 1. Zachar. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>ſtandeth before the Lord amongſt his ſeruants; but it is to accuſe, ſlaunder, and picke aduauntages againſt Gods people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I perſwade my ſelfe that the wiſedome of you (graue fathers) can marke out ſuch, better then I deſcribe them. And ye the learned cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors that are interpreters of the lawe, of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite and conſcience, will be loath to open their mouthes in the gates, for ſuch turbule<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuiters.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:26599:41"/> Yet (giue me leaue) no cauſe is ſo deſperate, no client ſo peruerſe, that findeth not a ſolicitor, at the leaſt, to helpe enuie forwarde, and pull iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice backward, if there be wilfulneſſe, and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liltie in the follower. Notwithſtanding I am aſſured, that the beſt for counſaile, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, amongſt you, deteſt both the contenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous quarrellers, and all thoſe brokers of ill cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that by ſhifts and quillets diſturbe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Courts of Iuſtice, and turne whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>Iudgement</hi> into <hi>bitter wormewood.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as the lawe is a comfortable baulme, to plaiſter vp the woundes and ſores of euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate diſquiet, with conuenient expedition: ſo (with all due reuerence to Gods ordinance be it ſpoken) are the delayes, quirkes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murres, like the corroſiue plaiſters of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable leach, which turne a ſmall greene wound into an incurable Fiſtula, by poiſoning and exulcerating the ſame, for their further practiſe and lucre. But I ſpeake in vaine, if I di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect my ſpeach to theſe kinde of people, who are not preſent in this place now, for the church is as the ſhadow of death vnto them, and they haue earneſt buſineſſe, which they loue aboue their ſoules. To you therefore prudent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, and all that feare God, be it ſpoken. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 5. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>that as vengeance is Gods,</hi> ſo the <hi>lawes are Gods, Iudgement is Gods, Counſell is Gods, verdict and ſentence are Gods.</hi> He that hath ſaid,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:26599:42"/> 
                     <hi>Iudge righteouſlie,</hi> hath ſayde alſo; <hi>Speake the thinges that are right. The tongue of the iuſt is</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rou. 10. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>as refined ſiluer</hi> ſayeth <hi>Salomon.</hi> There is no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth, no ſhift, no droſſe in it. The preſence of Gods Maieſty in iudgement, ingrauen in the browes of his Commiſſioners, calleth for reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſpeach: it admitteth no railing nor gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to obſcure the truth: nor thoſe anſweres <hi>ad hominem, non ad rem:</hi> that are to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſomewhat: but nothing to the purpoſe; though ſuch pleading in diſgrace of parties get a popular applauſe for the time. A cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine<note place="margin">Plut. apotheg.</note> of <hi>Darius</hi> hearing a mercenarie ſouldier to rayle againſt <hi>Alexander,</hi> in high wordes, ſtrooke him with his ſpeare, ſaying, <hi>Ego te vt pugnes &amp;c.</hi> I preſt thee to fight with <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and not to raile againſt him. And ſo do wiſe and honeſt clients retain aduocates, &amp; ſee them to plead their cauſe, not to reuile their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. O how ſweet are thoſe riches that are got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a good conſcience, and a tongue of ſound counſell, and pure wiſdome: <hi>But the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>of treaſure by a deceiptfull tongue, is as vanitie toſſed to and fro, of them that ſeeke death. He that coueteth that euill couetouſneſſe to build his houſe, conſulteth ſhame to his houſe,</hi> ſayeth <hi>Abacuk, for the ſtone ſhall crie out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber ſhall anſwere it with a woe,</hi> ringing aloude in the conſcience<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Haba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> of the founder himſelfe, laying the foundation
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:26599:42"/> in bloud and iniquitie.</p>
                  <p>I would thoſe buſie bodies, that abuſe the law, and your patience (right worſhipfull) with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, and ſlanderous actions, as alſo thoſe cruell tyrants, that crouch before authoritie <hi>to make the poore fall into their ſnares,</hi> and to rack the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of<note place="margin">Pſal. 10. 10.</note> ſpight, by extremities of law, were as well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with their dutie, as I know the better ſort here preſent is. But it is your partes (graue fathers) to quiet theſe ſtirring heads, &amp; quench theſe fierie ſpirits. All lawes both of God and men, haue prouided againſt the ſlanderous ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller, and cruell oppreſſor. <hi>Thou ſhalt not walke about with tales among the people: Thou ſhalt not ſtand againſt the bloud of thy neighbour, I am the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leuit. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord: that is the diuine law.</hi> Mens lawes were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, but the <hi>Athenians</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> prouided againſt them, ſome by baniſhment: ſome by penalties, ſome by an oath taken of the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe,<note place="margin">Wolſius in Deut. 22.</note> that he did follow no ſuit, <hi>animo calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andi,</hi> with a purpoſe of cauill and ſlaunder.</p>
                  <p>And for thoſe cruell tygres, that are all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with prickles like the Hedgehogge, that<note place="margin">Totus Ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inus aſper.</note> ſeeme to giue place to Gods holy wrath, and yet haue ſeauen abhominations in their hearts, and a thirſt to torment and impoueriſh their aduerſarie; theſe, I ſay, it becommeth your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms to diſcerne and diſcomfit. They are ſuch indeed as tarry the leiſure of the law, and ſeeke the face of the Court: but they wring the noſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:26599:43"/> to force out bloud, they houer after extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, forfeytures, and aduauntages,: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obtained; they themſelues catch their deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour<note place="margin">Matth. 18. 28.</note> by the throat, helpe to ſerue their owne executions, <hi>enter into the gates of him that is</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Obadiah. 1. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>fallen,</hi> delighting in his aduerſitie, and taking pleaſure in his miſerie, or elſe feeding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with a wicked triumph ouer the bones of a poore captiue ſtarued in priſon. Is this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to Gods holy will? who charged his people, that they ſhould <hi>not rule cruelly ouer</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Leuit. 25. 43.</note> 
                     <hi>their brethren ſolde vnto them:</hi> who in the 24. of <hi>Deuteronomium,</hi> commaunded them, <hi>when</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 24. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>they asked againe of their neighbor the thing that was lent, that they ſhould not go into his houſe to fetch a pledge, nor keepe the pledge till the Sunne went downe, of the partie that was poore;</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the 58. of <hi>Iſaie,</hi> mocketh at the faſtes and prayers of ſuch, as would ſeeme <hi>to bee deisout,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 58. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſerue God, and aske after the ordinaunces of the Lord, and yet they would ſeeke their owne will, and require all their debts,</hi> and <hi>ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſſe; when the Lord required a faſt from ſtrife, debate, &amp; extremitie; a looſing of the bands of wickedneſſe, a taking away of heauie burdens, a manumiſſion of the oppreſſed, and a breach of the yoke of bondage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As the vſurer, may be called a legall theefe,<note place="margin">Barnard. de cura rei fa.</note> becauſe hee couereth his cruell extortion by lawe: ſo may theſe vnmercifull creditors bee
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:26599:43"/> tearmed legall murtherers, ſuch as the lawe in ſome things doth aſſiſt: ſo that by law they may both go to the diuell togither, for their vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable mindes, as well as other theeues, &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers without law, for their vnlawful actions.</p>
                  <p>Amongſt other faults that the <hi>Corinthians</hi> are reproued for, by ſaint <hi>Paule,</hi> this was no ſmall one; that there were many quarrelles, ſuites, and complaints, commenced amongſt them, for <hi>ſmall matters,</hi> and that before <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Iudges,</hi> where they made themſelues ridiculous, and the Chriſtian profeſſion ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous, to them that were without. He tenteth their wound, and ſheweth what roote thoſe corruptions did ſpring from. For there wanted firſt <hi>wiſdome</hi> amongſt them, to compound and decide controuerſies. <hi>Is there not a wiſe man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>you?</hi> ſaith he; none that can find where the fault is, and ſet downe the right of the cauſe of ſo ſmall a moment? Secondly, there wanted loue; <hi>for brother with brother went to law, and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>that vnder Infidels.</hi> Thirdly, they wanted pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: <hi>Why rather ſuffer ye not wrong,</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 7.</note> one another, forgiue one another? let ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie faults paſſe, forget many iniuries, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to God? Fourthly, there wanted Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: <hi>Nay, ye your ſelues</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will do wrong, and harme, &amp; that to your brethren.</hi> Theſe foure wants muſt needes be amongſt vs (beloued) who are ſo litigious, and readie to go to the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:26599:44"/> law. For want of iuſtice <hi>in foro conſcientiae,</hi> in the Court of our conſcience, wee doe iniuries: for lacke of patience, we will ſuffer none: for want of loue, we ſpare neither father, nor brother: for lacke of wiſedome we come to no ſpeedie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement our ſelues, but the law muſt trie all. Out of Saint <hi>Paules</hi> reproofe, may it not well be thus ſpoken to you that are ſuch ſookers in law ſuits? Though ye haue not a conſcience to do right, nor patience to ſuffer wrong: nor loue to forbeare your brethren; yet if you were wiſe your ſelues, or had wiſe neighbours about you, your matters might bee determined at home. And doubtleſſe, if me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would do as they would be done to: or if the offender would <hi>agree with his aduerſarie quickly, in the way:</hi> and the partie<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> offended accept of reconciliation, and debate the matter with his neighbour himſelfe: what quiet of heart, and ſafegarde of monye, and godlye loue might bee procured? whereas now men dwell in ſuites, toſſing themſelues as in a ſea of troubles, enriching the lawyers, abuſing the lawe, and empoueriſhing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. It is a token of an vnholſome ayre,<note place="margin">Si valeans ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> mines, ars tua (Phoebe) iaces.</note> where the countrie is full of thriuing Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And <hi>Plato</hi> that diuine heathen ſayth, <hi>Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt profligatae, turpiſque educationis in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitate,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Danoeus ex Platone.</note> 
                     <hi>cum multis Iudicibus, iuriſconſultis, &amp; foris egeat. Reſpub.</hi> It is a ſigne of badde and wicked education, and ill maners in any
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:26599:44"/> countrie, when the Common-wealth hath neede of manie Iudges, manie Lawyers, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Courtes. The multitude of theſe Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our eſtate, ſo encreaſing, and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, telleth vs with ſhame that wee are a ſight of wrangling Chriſtians, for the moſt part, without iuſtice, without patience, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loue, and wiſedome: and therefore it is more then high time, that this were amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in thoſe that feare God, and reſpect the peace of a good conſcience. One great meanes of Reformation herein, reſteth in you (Right worſhipfull) if you carefullye put in practiſe that prudent example of <hi>Gallio</hi> depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in <hi>Achaia,</hi> who beeing importuned by the clamourous outcryes of <hi>Paules</hi> aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes; draue them all from the Iudgement<note place="margin">Acts. 18. 16.</note> ſeate, as men hauing more malice then mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. A commendable action in him that was but a heathen, but better will it become the place and profeſſion of a Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
                  <p>And thus, dearelie beloued, haue we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and ſerued this writte of prohibition agaynſt priuate reuenge, wee haue conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the louing title, vſed by Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure our heartes to a like proportion of loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againe. Wee haue heard how daungerous to our bodies, and ſoules, how preiudicial to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in both the exerciſe of hearing &amp; praying,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:26599:45"/> and what an enimie to God, and a friend and follower of the diuell, is a heart full of malice. And yet when iniquitie hath conceiued, and brought forth reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, either in words or deeds, then is it more daungerous: for as it hurteth it ſelfe firſt, ſo it miſchieueth others, being come to that paſſe. We haue gaged the poyſon of a wicked tongue, and found it vnmeaſurable; we haue applied meanes of cure if the patients will endure it: we haue arreſted all thoſe, and bound them to the peace, that dare vndertake their priuate reuenge, or proceede to the ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of a publike mutinie. If they will not obey our writ from heauen, we leaue them to you (right worſhipfull) the miniſters of Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, to be bent or broken. We haue direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all plaintiffes from their weake anger, to the mightie wrath of God: for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion royall of our prohibition from heauen, we haue brought a true copie, warranted by Saint <hi>Paule</hi> a faithfull Regiſter, of that ſacred Patent and Charter, wherin the Lord maketh knowne his chalenge, and threatneth not onely reuenge to all vſurpers, and euill doers, but promiſeth alſo a recompence to thoſe that abide his ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and commit their cauſe to him; or his miniſters ordained for reuenge &amp; recompenſe. Wee haue ſhewed what Magiſtrates are, and ſhould be: Gods they are for God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould not be rigorous, nor flouthfull, but
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:26599:45"/> iuſt, mercifull and diligent. We haue declared that ſubiectes cannot be well gouerned with oppreſſion of the greater: nor magiſtrates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by rebellion of the leſſe. We haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the abſurd opinions of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that would haue no ſuperiours, but all equalles; nothing priuate, but all things common; no lawes, but all luſt and libertie. We haue merte with thoſe foxes that vſe the publike ordinance of God, to racke their priuate ſpight, &amp; worke their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities. To conclude, we haue vſed motiues to diſſwade men both from priuate courſes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge; and alſo from the abuſe of that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vengeance, thoſe lawes, and that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which the Lord hath planted to preſerue the good, to maintaine peace, trueth &amp; right amongſt men. Now therefore (Graue fathers) remember your publike callings, that your ſword, and your ſentence, your iudgement &amp; vengeance is the Lords: Remember that by title you are Gods: but forget not your priuate condition; you ſhall dye like men: remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that you are maiſters and Iudges here, but forget not that you haue a maiſter and a Iudge in heauen Looke vpon the people, and thinke, though they be many as the blades of the field, yet are they but graſſe: <hi>all fleſh is graſſe, ſurely</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſaie. 40. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>the people are graſſe:</hi> but yet looke againe, and beholde that as the graſſe is, ſo is the flower alſo: as the people are, ſo are the Rulers: there
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:26599:46"/> is ſome difference in beautie and dignitie, as there is in the flower and the graſſe: but the graſſe withereth, &amp; the flower fadeth: men dye, and mortall Gods, like men periſh, but <hi>the word of God endureth for euer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To be ſhort, let all that feare God, obey this precept of his; renounce the purſuite of their owne malice, purge their hearts, and cleanſe their hands, giue place to his ordinance, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence his Miniſters, ſeeke lawfull remedies v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon neceſſitie: but ſeeke not ſo reuenge in this world, as though thou wouldeſt leaue nothing to be reuenged of God, in another. Deſpiſe not Gods vengeance here on earth: neither faint, nor be aſtonied though thy cauſe can not bee heard, though thy right cannot be cleared: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale in prayers to the witneſſe and Iudge of heauen: he is higher than the higheſt, euen that king of kings, that God of Gods, that Lord of lords, whoſe great name is heere ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to the claime and promiſe of trueth: <hi>vengeance is mine, I will repay</hi> ſaith the Lord: to whome being one in ſubſtance, three in perſon, the onely wiſe, inuiſible, and eternall God, be all honor, power and dominion for euer and euer,</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26599:46"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26599:47"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26599:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE SWORDE OF MAINTENANCE.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon preached before the <hi>Right Worſhipfull the Iudges of</hi> Aſſiſe, and gentlemen, aſſembled at <hi>Hertford, the 13. of Iuly</hi> 1599 for the execution of Iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
                  </p>
                  <figure>
                     <q>PERIIT ET INVENTA EST</q>
                     <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Barker</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>LONDON, <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Printed by R. B. for <hi>Gregory Seaton.</hi> 1600.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26599:48"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:26599:48"/>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>The text.</bibl>
                     <q>Hate the euill, and loue the good, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Iudgement in the gate: it may be<note place="margin">Amos. 5. 15.</note> that the Lord God of hoſtes will be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto the remnant of Ioſeph.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Neede not vſe many circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces (Right worſhipfull Fathers and brethren beloued in the Lord) to moue this graue aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to attention, whoſe religious mindes are readily prepared (I truſt) to receiue with meekenes the worde of God: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot but affourd mee beneuolent audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the handling of the matter of this text, being ſo conſonant to your godly diſpoſitions, pertinent to the preſent occaſion, and ſet downe in compendious precepts, ſo fit for your ſharpe vnderſtanding &amp; ſhort allowance of time.</p>
                  <p>For what elſe is my text, but a briefe iſſue of a long Proceſſe betweene the Lord of hoſtes &amp; his people? Who like a plaintiffe much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieued,<note place="margin">Amos. 3.</note> had often proteſted againſt the rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and made many proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (as with ſound of trumpet) againſt their iniuries offered: reproued their corruptions of<note place="margin">Amos. 4.</note>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:26599:49"/> religion, and their defaults of Iuſtice, cut downe their mightie ſinnes with mightie iudgements &amp; executions of famine, ſword &amp; peſtilence, thereby hauing waſted their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude from thouſands to hundreds, from hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds<note place="margin">Am. 5.</note> to tennes: and yet now as a kinde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intending the correction and not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of his children, hee offereth a capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of peace, with theſe conditions. If you will ſeeke the Lord, and liue, if you will ſeeke good and not euill, chuſe life and not death: hate his enemies, loue his friends, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſh his approued ordinance of iudgement: abandon all places of idolatry, ſurceaſe thoſe loftie ſinnes of oppreſſion and iniuſtice, ſo commonly practiſed in the gate, then goe to, the Lord will reaſon with you, and come to a friendly <hi>parle</hi> for further reconciliation. But before any peace can be concluded, mercie expected, puniſhment releaſed, or executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtayed: you muſt condiſcend to theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles: <hi>Hate the euill and loue the good, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh iudgement in the gate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In theſe wordes we may generally note theſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> two pointes: Firſt what conditions the Lord <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> requireth: Secondly what truce hee offereth. The conditions concerne the affections and actions: the affections are hatred and loue, each of them being directed vnto his ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obiect: hatred is let looſe at euill: loue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26599:49"/> is drawne and confined wholly to the good. The action is mixt, including many vertues, excluding many vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, being an accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of iuſtice and mercy, and the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of iudgement, whoſe fountaine is in the heart, and priuate affections of men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: but the ſtreames do flowe, &amp; runne downe in publike to the comfort of the good, and terrour of the badde. Theſe are the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles which the Lord doth propounde to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by his Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> and daily by vs his Ambaſſadors doth offer vnto you his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5</note> with deſire that you would be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled vnto him, and ſubſcribe with heart and hand to the contents thereof. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing promiſed, and performed, beholde a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious truce and couenant on Gods behalfe: <hi>It may be the Lord of hoſtes will be mercifull to the remnant of Ioſeph.</hi> Let no man be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged at this phraſe of ſpeach, as though Gods promiſes were like the doubtful Oracles of heatheniſh Idoles, yea and nay: it may be, and it may not be: for with the Lord there is aſſurance of mercie, his wordes be <hi>yea,</hi> and <hi>Amen. Hath hee ſaide it,</hi> and <hi>shall hee not doe it? hath hee spoken, and shall hee not accomplishe it?</hi> The poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties<note place="margin">Numb. 23.</note> of men are full of hazard, but the Lord <hi>is not a man that hee should lye or double,</hi> or be preuented of his purpoſe. Is there no
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:26599:50"/> doubt then in this ſpeach? None, touching the abſolute performance of the Lord: but much difficultie in reſpect of fleſh and bloud, if men looke vpon their owne vnworthineſſe, vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant perſeuerance, and the lowe ebbe that the houſe of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and Gods people are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times driuen vnto. Yet againe, all is courage, when we caſt our eyes vpon the Lord of hoſts who is ſtrong to ſaue, inclyning to mercy, whoſe readineſſe to helpe in extremitie appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Ioſeph;</hi> and was often ſhewed to his ſeed, when they were but a remnant and reuerſion: and therefore may aſſuredly comfort all faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full hearts that without all doubt, hee will be mercifull vnto them, if they keepe this coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Lord, and conſent to hate the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and loue the good, and eſtabliſh iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the gate.</p>
                  <p>Thus much haue I ſpoken to declare vppon what ground our doctrine &amp; exhortations (by Gods aſſiſtance) ſhall be planted: in what tearmes the eſtate of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen ſtoode: and what Articles were propounded for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of their calamities: in the vrging &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folding whereof, our greateſt time ſhall be ſpent; becauſe we deſire to apply the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued remedy to our owne decayes, &amp; wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, aſſuring our ſelues the Lord will not faile to be mercifull, if we keepe touch and promiſe with him, in ſuch conditions as he requireth.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:26599:50"/>
                  <p>In one word therefore to winde vp the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of all theſe conditions: it is that which wee<note place="margin">Knowledge. 1</note> call ſometimes conſcience, ſometimes zeale; not the common conſcience of the world: but that ſame which is firſt <hi>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcientia,</hi> ioyned with knowledge, that it may haue an eye to diſcerne<note place="margin">Courag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2.</note> good from euill. Secondly that which is roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and planted in the will and affections, that it may haue an edge of hatred to threaten the euill: and a backe of loue to defend the good.<note place="margin">Practiſe. 3.</note> Thirdly ſuch a conſcience here is required, as hath not onely ſkill to diſcerne or will to deſire, but alſo a readie hand to practiſe: not reſting in contemplation, but proceeding to ſuch action as the place and vocation of euery man exhorteth him vnto for the maintenance of <hi>iudgement in the gate.</hi> Theſe three proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a good conſcience, called by the Lord, in this text, and aſpired vnto by all that feare God, or loue the good eſtate of their country, amongſt this graue aſſembly, occaſion mee to ſpeake ſomewhat of eyther, and firſt of knowledge.</p>
                  <p>Knowledge is the guide and light of a good<note place="margin">1. Knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> conſcience. A fit Intelligencer for the will and affections, for it aduiſeth what is euill and to be eſchewed, what is good and to be embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Without this direction, hatred like a <hi>blinde archer ſhootes beſide the marke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and may kill a man in ſteade of a beaſt:</hi> And loue cheriſheth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:26599:51"/> often a ſnake in the boſome, in ſteade of a friende. As the eye diſcernes betweene light and darkeneſſe, ſo the vnderſtanding tryeth out the difference betweene good and euill. Therefore <hi>ſeeke good, and not euill</hi> ſayd the Prophet in the former verſe. No man can ſeeke well without light, nor finde the good except hee can diſtinguiſh it from the badde, and trying all hold that which is the beſt.</p>
                  <p>Many are the difficulties that hinder vs from the diſcouery of euill, and the recouery of the good: and yet great is the daunger, if wee miſtake the one for the other.</p>
                  <p>The difficulties appeare if wee conſider firſt<note place="margin">Difficult.</note> the blindneſſe of our owne heart, except it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> be renewed and ſupplyed with a light from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> heauen. Secondly if wee beholde the readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of euill, being preſent with vs at euery turne, <hi>compaſſing vs about, preſſing vs downe,</hi> Satan as <hi>a prince in the ayre</hi> tempting vs, <hi>a worlde of ſinne</hi> about vs, <hi>a bodie of ſinne</hi> within vs. Beſides this, the cuſtome of ſinne hath <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> made vertue ſo vnpleaſant and ſtraunge; the euil ſo ſweete &amp; familiar, that it ſeemeth death to be rowzed out of the myre, wherein wee haue long wallowed in eaſe and ſecuritie. And <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> further: iniquitie is very ſtrong, being in this world, as in her owne country, and proper e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, where vertue is but a ſtraunger, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26599:51"/> flying vpward, and therefore not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with halfe ſo many ſchollers as ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, that pulles downe the hill to the broad gates of hell and deſtruction. Laſtly euill <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> is mingled with the good, as droſſe with the ſiluer, that it aſketh much tryall, and a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit to extract the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In regarde of which difficulties hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our choyce in the good, and preſenting to the luſt of our eyes varietie and chaunge of euill, in goodly ſhapes of apparant good, it behoueth vs to haue a ſounde vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for our guide: but eſpecially becauſe the error of our choyce is the danger both of ſoule<note place="margin">Daunger.</note> and bodie.</p>
                  <p>The fruite of the forbidden tree was pleaſaunt to beholde, and good to eate, but it was bitterneſſe and death at the laſt. For euill is of two ſortes, the ſeede and the fruit; the ſeede is ſinne, and the fruite is puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the one is a ſweete baite, the other a deadely hooke: <hi>it goes downe pleaſantly like wine, but it ſtingeth in the end like a Scorpion.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 23. 31.</note> And yet there is a league betwene iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and our affections, as there was betweene <hi>Iezabel</hi> and her chamberlaines: As <hi>Ieſabel</hi> pearching aloft, painted her face, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">2 King. 9. 30.</note> her Eunuches attending vpon her, til <hi>Iehu,</hi> ſent with reuenge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, began to cry, <hi>who is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26599:52"/> on my ſide? who?</hi> So doth iniquitie poſſeſſe the higheſt chamber of our heart, and paints her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in freſh coloures, raigning ouer our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections as ſlaues, till vengeance hunt after her ſteppes, and the meſſengers of God giue war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the affections, to caſt downe their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed miſtreſſe, and renounce that ſinne, which they haue ſerued, leaſt the fall of her, dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>we all her Eunuches and partakers to confuſion.</p>
                  <p>The heathens themſelues alwaies taught o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the will to the wit, of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to reaſon: which had beene well, if the light of reaſon had not beene extinguiſhed in heauenly things: and ſo fowly blemiſhed in naturall. <hi>But the naturall mans reaſon perceiuing not the things of God</hi> (his <hi>wiſdome being foliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> his <hi>light darkeneſſe</hi>) made the conſcience corrupt and vaine in the trewe and particular diſcourſe of good and euill. Many ſay: <hi>who will ſhewe vs any good?</hi> ſaide <hi>Dauid</hi> of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon<note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 6.</note> ſort: but he muſt haue a new ſpirit and a perfect vnderſtanding, that with <hi>Dauid</hi> can lift his eyes to heauen, and cry: <hi>Lord lift thou vp the light of thy cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance;</hi> acknowledging al our felicity to depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fauour of the Lord. In matters of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon honeſty, humanitie, ciuilitie of manners, the heathens were a lawe to themſelues, and ſhall be a ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> to vs: in that with ſo ſmall a glimſe of naturall light, they practiſed many thinges
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:26599:52"/> commendable, made many wholſome lawes, excelled in many outward cenſures, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of indgement. But wee hauing the <hi>word</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>of the Lord, conuerting the ſoule, giuing wiſdome to the ſimple, and light to the eyes:</hi> hauing the lawe of God (I ſay) to examine what is good, and what euill, being the onely touchſtone of trueth and falſehoode, the rule that ſheweth as wel the crooked as the ſtraight: If wee <hi>loue darkeneſſe rather than light,</hi> if wee faile in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſetting vp the kingdome of God, or the righteouſneſſe thereof in our life and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: there remaineth vnto vs no colour of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, nor cloke of defence. For vnto euery one of vs in our ſeuerall charge, may that proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Micah</hi> be vrged: <hi>Hee hath ſhewed thee (O man) what is good, and what the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Micah. 6. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>of thee: ſurely to doe iuſtly, and to loue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and to humble thy ſelfe, and to walke with thy God.</hi> And this is that <hi>knowledge</hi> of good &amp; euill, deriued out of Gods holy and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table will and word, which like a cunning ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der turneth, and directeth our affections be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of themſelues like <hi>horſe and mule that haue no vnderſtanding.</hi> But as the Lord inſtructeth<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> all Rulers to be wiſe and learned, ſo in another place he will haue them in the <hi>feare of God, to</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 18. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>be men of courage</hi> alſo. For <hi>courage</hi> is the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uencie<note place="margin">Courage.</note> and concitation of the minde placed here in theſe two affections, <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>loue:</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:26599:53"/> which are profitable to the furtherance of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and taking downe of vice, ſo as they ſtand in awe of reaſon, as a ſouldier of his captaine, by whoſe commaunde hee takes vp and layes downe both his courage and<note place="margin">Baſi, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Jraſc.</note> weapons. Wherefore theſe affections are not onely to be allayed and cooled in man (as ſome Philoſophers affirme) but ſometimes<note place="margin">Peripatet.</note> alſo to bee kindled and ſtirred vp: that as the iron is ſteeled and hardned with the fire,<note place="margin">Baſ.</note> ſo mans heart with concitation of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites againſt the right obiect may haue a tincture of greater courage and fortitude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt GODS enemies. Neither is this agreeable to the opinion of the <hi>Stoickes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lactant. Iuſt. lib. 6. cap. 14.</note> who vtterly extinguiſhed all ſparkes of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, in their vertuous and perfect man, pulling out both gall and bowels as though there coulde bee no good vſe of them, for the exerciſe of vertue. For indeede it is an extremitie of ſinne, to haue a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red conſcience, that feeles no prickes of humanitie: and a token of a reprobate ſenſe to be ſenſeleſſe, and without naturall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Rom. 1. 30.</note> Neither againe hath our firſt creation planted any malignant nature in the minde of man (as the <hi>Manicheis</hi> dreamed:) nor yet by<note place="margin">Auguſt. confeſſ. lib. 8. cap. 10. Illyricus.</note> the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> is there a diueliſh ſubſtance of miſchiefe poſſeſſing the ſoule of man: but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26599:53"/> the ſame principles that were created pure and good, and corrupted in qualitie only, by that afterclappe of our forefather: being refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and altered by the ſpirit of GOD, are to be employed in Gods holy ſeruice: hatred in the purſuite of euill, loue in the defence of vertue and goodneſſe. By theſe therefore, as by the two ſupporters. Iuſtice is aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, the ſcepter of Princes gouerned, the ſworde of magiſtrates kept vpright, king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes eſtabliſhed, Gods Church and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth preſerued.</p>
                  <p>Seeing the Lord reacheth the affections, and ſetteth the inward parts firſt on worke, in the deteſtation of euill, and fauour of the good: it appeares, that hee condemnes all hypocriſie, that gliſtereth in ſome eye-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, but acteth nothing heartily: and that hee excludeth all thoſe diſſembling Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, which <hi>Machiauel</hi> painteth out in ſome outwarde coloures and ſhadowes of Iuſtice, but inwardly full of all diueliſh ſubtiltie. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are thoſe qualified according to this rule, that ſeparate the Serpents wiſdome from the doues innocencye. <hi>Achitophels</hi> counſell, though it be like the Oracles of<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16. 23.</note> GOD for worldly witte, and the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt it was in: yet being like myſteries of the diuel for diſhoneſty, &amp; miſchieuous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26599:54"/> is rather curſed then bleſſed by the Lord: for his condition is to haue wiſdome matched with holineſſe, a iuſt conuerſation with a good conſcience: an vpright heart, fearing God, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing euill, approuing the thing that is good, with a conſtant purpoſe in himſelfe &amp; others to deſtroy the power of Satan braunch and roote, and aduance the kingdome of God with the righteouſneſſe thereof.</p>
                  <p>It is ſtraunge to beholde what a ſpirit of gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe, confuſion and ſlumber ſometimes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth the minde &amp; conſciences of many that haue had ſome knowledge diſcerning betwene good and euill, but haue wanted this ſanctified hatred of the one, and feruent loue to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. What made that neutralitie of religion in <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi> that men feared God, and<note place="margin">2. King. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1. King. 18. Zephan. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>yet worſhipped their idoles?</hi> halted between <hi>God &amp; Baall?</hi> vſed to ſweare by the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cham?</hi> It was not ſimple ignorance of the true religion, but want of zealous and heartie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of Idolatry, ſelfe-wil-worſhippe, &amp; hypocriſie. And how is it come to paſſe, that amongſt vs, after ſo much preaching, &amp; ſo great light, ſo many ſtand at a gaze in religion; waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring betweene <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Canaan,</hi> betweene Chriſt and Antichriſt, light and darkeneſſe? Or what is the cauſe that in the wombe of our mother the Church of England, there are bredde ſuch corrupt children, as account all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26599:54"/> religion either a publike policie; or terme all hatred of ſinne, loue of trueth; reformation of the life, ſtudie of pietie, and practiſe of modeſtie but an humour? and a fancie follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the complexion? Doubtleſſe theſe men haue had knowledge of the good and bad: but ſome of them haue made no carefull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of the poyſon from the wholſome<note place="margin">2. King. 4. 40.</note> fruite, and therefore <hi>death is in the pot:</hi> ſome perceiuing <hi>iniquitie to abound, and the loue of</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 24. 12. Reuel. 2. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>many waxing cold, became luke-warme and loſt their firſt loue for companie.</hi> Others hauing had neuer any loue indeede to the truth, or hatred of vngodlineſſe, are giuen ouer to<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 11.</note> beleeue lyes in the blindeneſſe and luſtes of their owne ſenſe, and peruerſe imagination. Who although they haue bene ſhuffled with Chriſtians, as <hi>Saul</hi> amongſt the Prophets, by reaſon of lawes and orders, for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 19. 24.</note> yet are they ſuch as neuer haue made any <hi>couenant in heart with the Lord, to hate</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>the euill, and loue the good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As in matters of religion, ſo in ciuill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour and outwarde iuſtice, behold (Right worſhipfull) the like effectes of the like<note place="margin">Ierem. 9. 3.</note> negligence; when men haue <hi>no courage for the trueth, they proceede from euill to worſe;</hi> as though they had no knowledge, neither of right or wrong, good or euill.</p>
                  <p>Such was the ſottiſhneſſe of <hi>Nabal</hi> in the<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25. 10.</note>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:26599:55"/> middeſt of his plentie, that hee knewe not his friende from his foe, made no difference betweene <hi>Dauid,</hi> that had beene as a <hi>well to his ſeruantes,</hi> and ſome common fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,<note place="margin">1. Sam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 25. 17.</note> that had <hi>runne away from his maſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hee growes ſo wicked at laſt that a man may</hi>
                     <note place="margin">37.</note> 
                     <hi>not ſpeake to him,</hi> and as hee liued like a blocke, ſo hee dyes like a ſtone in the ende. Many, in the <hi>Preachers</hi> time, were come to that paſſe, that they made no diſtinction betweene the conditions of the Iuſt and the<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9. 12.</note> wicked, the pure and polluted, the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and him that feared an oath. And what ſay the obſtinate and wilfull people in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie? Wee count the proude bleſſed, and them</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Malach. 3. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>that worke wickedneſſe.</hi> Nay, in our age what difference doe many make of the trueth and a lye, of deceipte and vpright dealing, of whordome, and vndefiled marriage, of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie and honeſt trade, of ſtolne breade and the breade of labour? the taſte is the ſame, all gaine is godlineſſe; all money ſauoureth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. O fearefull ſhipwracke of faith and a good conſcience; GOD and <hi>Mammon,</hi> hell and heauen, light and darkneſſe are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall matches in their lumpiſhe vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
                  <p>In all eſtates and degrees where there is a defect of courage and zeale, ſuch fruites
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26599:55"/> ſpring vp by little and little; as indeede <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo repente fuit turpiſſimus:</hi> no man at the<note place="margin">Iuuenal.</note> firſt ſteppe came to the height of iniquitie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <note place="margin">Barnard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidi dom. Ecclus. 27. 11.</note> The miniſter that ſhines without heate, as he giues no great light, ſo he is not of any great certaintie, but <hi>is changed like the Moone:</hi> And<note place="margin">Luke. 14. 35.</note> hee that hath no ſalt to powder his wordes, waxeth altogither vnſauourie at the laſt, and <hi>ſcarſe good for the dunghill.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Magiſtrate whoſe conſcience affecteth not the due adminiſtration of iuſtice, groweth by degrees to be a ſleepie watchman, whoſe drowzie lethargie depriueth him of all ſenſe, &amp; diſtinction of good and euill, right or wrong: the extremitie of which incurable diſeaſe, is noted in two properties by our Sauiour Chriſt, of a <hi>Iudge that feared not God, nor reuerenced</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luke.</hi> 18. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>men.</hi> Experience teacheth vs, that a Bee which hath loſt his ſting becommeth an vnprofitable drone, neither fit to keepe, or gather honie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and a gouernour that hath neither courage nor zeale agaynſt ſinne, is vnmeete to preſerue vertue in her right, or maintaine iudgements A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>de is more fit for him then a rodde; and a ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t foyle to play withall, then a ſworde of Iuſtice to puniſh with.</p>
                  <p>The want of this zeale made that the faithfull<note place="margin">Iſai 1. 21. 22.</note> citie of the Lord became a harlot, their ſiluer became droſſe, &amp; the in <hi>wine was mixed with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, their Princes were rebellious, &amp; companions of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26599:56"/> theeues.</hi> A lamentable eſtate is it when the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections are miſplaced, and iudgement ſo tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp ſide downe, <hi>that men will ſpeake good of euill, and put darkneſſe for light, light for darknes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 5. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>bitter for ſweete, and ſweete for ſowre.</hi> A woe is pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced to thoſe prepoſterous dealers, that ſhuffle vp matters with ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And I take it a part of the woe, that they grow <hi>from euil to worſe,</hi> til they be ſo infatuated<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erem. 93.</note> that as they, like Idols regarded in conſcience neither right nor wrong: ſo like Epicures at laſt they meaſure the righteous Lord, and his iuſt iudgements, by the leaden rule of their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſenſes. <hi>Such will the Lord ſearch for, with a candle being frozen in their dregs, and ſaying in</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zephan. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Ezech. 9. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>their hearts; The Lord will do neither good nor euill.</hi> They ſleep, and dreame alſo that the Lord ſlumbreth: who notwithſtanding <hi>euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning bringeth his iudgement to light, and fayleth</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zephan. 3. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>not: but the wicked will not learne to be aſhamed,</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Zephanie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is no maruell therefore, that the Lord will haue the obſeruation of theſe conditions to be grounded in the affections; and from thence to breake out into publike action, and the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>iudgement in the gate:</hi> ſeeing that if the fountain head be intoxicate, the ſtreams wil be<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> infectious; or if the conſcience be ſeared vp, all other abſurdities &amp; confuſions of religion, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon humanity, &amp; iuſtice break in amongſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:26599:56"/>
                  <p>Behold therefore how theſe affections muſt worke to the eſtabliſhment of <hi>iudgement in our gates,</hi> or elſe what inconueniences follow: Firſt by negligence, where no gaine appeares; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by partialitie, when lucre is expected. Some that heare this precept vrged, <hi>hate the euill, loue the good,</hi> will approue of the loue, but repeale his hatred. It is pittie (ſay ſome) that faire weather ſhould do any harme; and yet for all this pitty, there muſt be foule as wel as faire. Loue, and faire meanes, gentle dealing (which they call onely loue) are good, but to whom? <hi>Meliores ſunt, quos dirigit amor</hi> (ſayth <hi>Auſten</hi>) they are the better ſort which will be directed by loue: <hi>ſed plures ſunt quos corrigit timor,</hi> but the greater part are not to be amended but by feare.</p>
                  <p>An olde feſtered ſore muſt not haue a le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue plaiſter. And it is true that an vnruly Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent maketh a cruel Phyſition. As the wine that is too hard is vnpleaſant: ſo that which is too flat is vnholſome. The Lord teacheth vs by his example, how to vſe theſe affections, although he be ſubiect to no paſſion himſelfe. <hi>Anger is not in me</hi> (ſayth he) when hee ſpeaketh to<note place="margin">Iſai. 27. 4.</note> his people. <hi>But if the briars and thornes were ſet agaynſt me in battaile, I would burne them,</hi> ſayth the ſame Lord, ſpeaking of his enimies. <hi>With the pure he is pure, with the froward he will ſhew</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>frowardnes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> attributing to the Lord
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26599:57"/> mercie and iudgement ſeeming contrarie by reaſon of the obiect he worketh vpon, yet iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the <hi>father of lights, in whom is no ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mes.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7.</note> 
                     <hi>of chaunge of contrarietie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Dauid</hi> being a kinde ſheepheard to Iſrael himſelfe, yet taketh witneſſe of the<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.</note> Lorde, that his thoughts hate euill: <hi>Do not I hate them that hate thee (O Lord) doe not I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with them that riſe vp againſt thee? Moſes</hi> was a verie meeke man; and yet with the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie of his people he is ſo incenſed, that hee breakes the tables of the Couenant, and then he crieth to execution. <hi>Euery man ſlay his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his companion, his neighbour:</hi> the fact per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> (ſayeth he) <hi>You haue conſecrated your handes this day to the Lord.</hi> So acceptable a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice is the puniſhment of Gods enemies, and euill doers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iob</hi> was <hi>an eye to the blinde, and a foote to the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 29. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>lame:</hi> and yet the ſame <hi>Iob</hi> maketh this try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of his earneſt purſuit of the wicked: <hi>I brake the chawes of the vngodly, and pluckt the prey out of their teeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lordes champion <hi>Dauid</hi> intended a rough c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re of intractable malefactors: when he threatned them, and armed himſelf after this maner: <hi>The wicked ſhall be euerie one as thornes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 23. 6. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>thruſt away, becauſe they cannot be taken with handes: but the man that ſhall touch them, muſt be defenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d with iron.</hi> Though the wicked bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulie,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26599:57"/> ſharpe, and daungerous to deale withall; yet the Lord hath armed your hands (graue fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) with iron gantlets, with authoritie from heauen, Commiſſion from the Prince, to gripe the proudeſt offender, to ſtrike the Lion and the Beare, the oppreſſor, extortioner, the rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and bloud-ſhedder, that the ſheepe and and harmleſſe people may bee reſcued from the vngodly, that are <hi>mightier then they.</hi> It was<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> vnſeaſonable pitie that <hi>Saul</hi> ſhewed in ſparing <hi>Agag</hi> the enemie of God, and Iſrael. And <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab</hi> did not wiſely, in yeelding ſuch fauour to <hi>Benhadad,</hi> appoynted by the Lord to die: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his ſeruants preſented themſelues with great humilitie <hi>in ſackcloth</hi> and <hi>halters,</hi> gloſing vpon the rehearſall of his wordes; <hi>thy brother Benhadad. Saul</hi> had a ſharpe rebuke for his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely pittie, and <hi>Achab</hi> threatned that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had let him go that was appoynted to die, therefore <hi>thy life for his life, thy people for his people,</hi> ſaid the Lord. Is it not needfull to ſhewe a deepe diſpleaſure againſt all notorious offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, if the Magiſtrate becomes not onely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable in his owne perſon, for the wilfull eſcape of Gods knowne enemie; but alſo the innocent people ſtand indicted, and are to bee puniſhed before the Lord, and to pay their liues a raunſome for the wicked eſcaped with impunity? and that but by one mans default. <hi>S. Auguſtin</hi> ſhewing why the good and bad, were
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26599:58"/> both enwrapped togither within the compaſſe of the ſelfe ſame ſcourge by the furious Gothes, yeeldeth this reaſon: <hi>Iure amaram vitam ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiunt;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ciuitat. Dei. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1. cap. 9.</note> worthily they feele the bitterneſſe of this life with the wicked, <hi>quia peccantibus amari eſſe noluerunt;</hi> becauſe they were not bitter to them in their ſinnes, but ouer gentle, hauing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fellowſhip with the workes of darkneſſe, then reprouing them. And this was the cauſe that father <hi>Eli</hi> was plagued as well as his<note place="margin">Sam. 2.</note> ſonnes, for his indulgence, and remiſſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of that whoredome and ſacriledge, which to the diſhonour of God, and ſcandall of the people they committed. For when ſinne groweth ſtoute and loftie, and puniſhmentes weake, when the rodde of Scorpions is turned into feathers, when priuate men reprooue not the vngodly, miniſters rebuke not, Iudges and rulers (hauing them offered) puniſh not, at the laſt all become guiltie, all actors and conſenters in ſinne, and all be puniſhed with a grand exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of ſome famine, peſtilence, ſworde, or ſuch like calamitie.</p>
                  <p>I would to God in our peaceable eſtate, there were no want of this holie indignation, and religious fortitude, in the purſuit of thoſe manifolde ſinnes which are the ſpottes of our peace, and ſhadowes in the ſunne-ſhine of the Goſpel. But ſet before your eyes (religious au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience) our whole eſtate: and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider (as I doubt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26599:58"/> not but you do ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) the ſores of our body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, and the breaches of our land, from the top of the head, to the ſoale of the foote, and you ſhall behold many wounds, and many ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne plaiſters, and yet very ſlow healing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there wanteth courage in the heart of the Phiſitions, to apply the one to the other. Looke downe to the legges of our Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and remember that lately they were ready to rot with idlenes &amp; miſery. Thoſe idle vagarants (I meane) who ſwarming like Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpillers not long ſince, and treading downe<note place="margin">Prou. 13. 23.</note> the fielde of the poore (wherein is much fruit if it bee well ordered) walking without checke or ſhame, in theft, drunkenneſſe, and whoredome, in prophaneneſſe of life, and all vngodlineſſe, ſwearing and curſing, lying and murthering, begetting a monſtrous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, (the parents without wedlocke, the children without baptiſme) are they not mightilye repreſſed by an eaſie medicine, wiſelie prouided by the ſuperiour powers? and yet but coldly applyed by the inferiour of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers? Who amongeſt vs, remembring the groſſe inconueniences of thoſe idle backes and ſlowe bellyes ſo tolerated to wnader and increaſe, but will deteſt that courſe of lyfe? And yet there muſt bee a reſpectiue looke of loue to Gods c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eatures, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration of them: for though they be lazie
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:26599:59"/> legges, and yet are they our limmes, and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers: and therefore to be ſupplied with worke, and reliefe, with direction and correction, by thoſe parts that carry the eyes, and wiſdome to gouerne and teach, As hatred of their ſinne is readie to whippe them: ſo loue and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion muſt be readie to helpe feede them. They muſt eate (ſo nature teacheth vs) not the bread of idleneſſe, but their owne bread, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by their labour, ſo the Scripture infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3. 12.</note> vs.</p>
                  <p>A wife and auncient Counſeller ſometime of this Realme, wittily rebuked the maners and orders of a ſtraunge Countrie, not much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note place="margin">Sir Th. More Vtop.</note> from his owne but in the title; <hi>for that they firſt made theeues, and taught them to ſteale, and after hanged them vp.</hi> They made theeues (ſaith he) in that they ſuffered ſuch a multitude of ſeruingmen, to bee trained vp in idleneſſe and pride: which after being thruſt out of ſeruice, muſt needes be driuen to theeuerie, for beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging they ſcorned, and to labour they had not learned in any honeſt vocation. I will not ſay but men made ſeruice able are verie neceſſarie, and ſtand before great men in good place: But idleneſſe, permitted to a multitude, muſt needs be the nurſerie of beggers, and where manie luſtie open beggers remaine, there, ſayth <hi>Plato,</hi> be many <hi>priuie theeues, and pickers.</hi> As all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<note place="margin">Plato de. rep. dial. 8. Zepper.</note> countryes are noted for ſome peculiar
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26599:59"/> vice, which the people thereof are moſt addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto: ſo Engliſh men though they be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genioſi,</hi> yet are they <hi>deſidioſi,</hi> though ingenious,<note place="margin">Aſcham.</note> yet idle; it is our fault, and therefore asketh great induſtrie of the gouernours, before it can be throughly expulſed. Neither is it to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten, that a renowmed King of this nation <hi>Edward, the third</hi> of that name, procured ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from beyond the ſeas, with great rewards<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Camden</hi> in Kent.</note> and priuiledges, to come into this countrie; and teach our people that trade of clothing, which to the great benefite of this lande, and employment of the poorer ſort, is yet in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: whence al our wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are preſuppoſed ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: as the men of meane degree are intended laborers. And ſure a kingly practiſe is it to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide worke for the luſtie and ſtrong, as reliefe and hoſpitalitie for the ſicke, and the lame. From the head there deſcende ſinewes to the hands, and inferiour members: and from the higheſt in place, muſt iſſue ſuch good directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as may gouerne the whole bodie, &amp; keepe it in frame. The legges muſt <hi>not be cut off, or</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb, 12. 12,</note> 
                     <hi>turned cleane out of the way, but rather ſtreight ſteppes are to be made to our feete, and the halting legges to be healed, and the feeble knees to be lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we aſcend from the legges to the handes: ſhall we not ſee a multitude of them defiled with bloodſhed, beſide the manifold iniquities
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26599:60"/> wherewith they are exerciſed? Compt the woundes, the murthers, and the bloud that is ſhedde in euerye part of our lande: note how it is couered vnder the wings of men that haue countenaunce: how it is pleaded for, with this allegation, that life is to be fauoured (euen in fauour of him that had no mercy in his rage) and we may with good cauſe be afrayde leaſt the Lord arraigne the whole land for bloud vnreuenged, crying in his eares. The life and bloud of the murtherer is owing to the Lord, who putteth the ſworde into the<note place="margin">Gene. 9. 6.</note> Magiſtrates hand to make payment and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for bloud wrongfully ſhedde: there is no way to purge the land from bloud, but to ſtrike the offender, <hi>that the righteous may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 58. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>and waſh his foote in the bloud of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: and make it a Caueat to keepe him from the like.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Looke vp towarde the heades, and greater men of our Common-wealth: If the want of diſcipline, ſuffred the Graſhoppers to catch a head which ſkip vpon the ground: what will not the Caterpillers dare that ſit aloft in the higheſt trees, amongſt much fruit, clothed in gay colours, deſpiſing the Magiſtrate, and ſcorning the Miniſter? There is indeed a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſeaſe very dangerous in many of them, that carrie ſomething high ſayles, and thinke themſelues to be mightie: which is called, <hi>Noli
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26599:60"/> me tangere,</hi> Touch me if thou dare. As in phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, ſo in diuinitie, it is thought to be incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: becauſe the more it is handled &amp; dealt withall, the more it ſwelleth and rageth with anger and fretfulneſſe.</p>
                  <p>This diſeaſe raigneth amongſt the vſurers and extortioners of our time, that <hi>hate the good,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Micha. 3. 23</note> 
                     <hi>and loue the euill, and plucke off the skinnes from the people, and the fleſh from their bones: that ioyne houſe to houſe, and field to field, till there</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 5. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>be no place, but for themſelues:</hi> that depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late whole townes, <hi>and ſwallow vp the poore that</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos. 8. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>the needie of the land may faile:</hi> and yet breake through the ſtatutes and lawes as through cobwebbes, which hamper the Flies, but yeeld place of euaſion to the Bees.</p>
                  <p>And are not many of the greater ſort farre gone with this diſeaſe, that will be blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers in their ſpeach as with authoritie? Their <hi>tongues be their owne, and who ſhall controll?</hi> Are<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.</note> not Lawes, and Church, and ſeruice of God, holineſſe and obſeruation of the Sabbaoth, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted exerciſes for meane men? Great men may doe what they luſt. Hard is the fire to be quenched that hath taken the top of the houſe: and how hard a thing is it, for wealthie men to reforme a vice? Who dare rebuke or reproue <hi>Herode,</hi> though he liue in inceſt and horrible<note place="margin">Marke. 6.</note> adultery? If <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſhal diſcharge his duty, by one meanes or other, at one time or another
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26599:61"/> it will hazard his life, Iudgements of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and reproofes of the Prophet, are not to come neere <hi>Bethel,</hi> and the Courtes of the<note place="margin">Amos. 7. 13.</note> mightie, as many ſuppoſe: yet muſt not wee ceaſe to warne and exhort, and threaten ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times: but you (right worſhipfull) who repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the Maieſtie of almightie God, and carry the authoritie of a godlie Prince: muſt eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially declare by the couragious execution of good lawes, how little you regarde the high lookes of the proud, and how much you hate iniquitie, and loue iudgement, mercie and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie.</p>
                  <p>You haue a <hi>Sworde of maintenance</hi> put into your handes, long enough to reach the moſt offences, both of high &amp; low: although in thoſe ſinnes of blaſphemie and adulterie, it ſeemes to be too ſhort. But though the ſwearer and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterer ſtand not in your Kalender condemned to die: yet the Lord ſayth of the one, <hi>He will not holde him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vaine:</hi> the other hee ſeemes to reſerue to his ſharper iudgement, becauſe he is here ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlipt: <hi>for whoremongers and adulterers God will</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>iudge,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle. And yet as a prince ſitting in iudgement chaſeth away all euil with his eyes: ſo with your lookes, and wordes of deteſtation comptroll, checke theſe faultes at leaſt, that your zeale and hatred againſt al ſuch euils may appeare.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:26599:61"/>
                  <p>Thus haue we ſharpned this holy hatred, and brought it to the eſtabliſhment of iuſtice in the gate: which notwithſtanding is not contrarie to loue, but rather a braunch of that roote. For as the Lordes chaſticements are the tokens of his loue: ſo are mens puniſhments the fruits of mercie and compaſſion. The good ſheepheard is cruell to the woolfe for the lambes ſafetie: and a good magiſtrate rigorous to the wicked for ſafegard of the meeke. There is <hi>Miſcricor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia puniens,</hi> and <hi>Crudelit as parcens;</hi> Pittie puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and crueltie ſparing: ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h that pitifull father <hi>Auſten,</hi> that yet ouermuch contendeth<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Macedon.</note> with the Magiſtrates of his time for the pardon of malefactors penitent.</p>
                  <p>But as the corrupt time and maners, require a concitation of anger, againſt iniquitie: ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be it prouided, that hatred and loue, iudgement and mercie, be knit togither in one linke: and ſit both togither as Iudges ioyned in one commiſſion. All lawes are not to bee written in bloud: nor euerie offender puniſhed alike, when neceſſarie circumſtances alter the caſe. They are cruell Surgeons that haue no other meanes of cure, but inciſion, burning, and launcing, for euerie ſore. <hi>There ſhall be iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment mercileſſe to him that ſheweth no mercie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iames. 2. 13.</note> ſayth <hi>Iames,</hi> and the wiſe man giueth this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat:<note place="margin">Eccles. 7. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Be not iuſt ouermuch.</hi> Equitie and not extremitie is to be practiſed, <hi>Be angry</hi> (ſaith the<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. 26.</note>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:26599:62"/> Apoſtle) <hi>and ſinne not:</hi> giuing the ſpurre to the affections: and yet adding a bridle withall, to keepe moderation.</p>
                  <p>And euen when ſinne, detected and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, doth enforce the Iudge to execution; then muſt he remember, that as he is a Iudge for God: ſo is he a man agaynſt man. <hi>Te habes ante te</hi> (ſayeth <hi>Auſten</hi>) Thou haſt a patterne of thy ſelfe before thy ſelfe. I can bring no better example of Iudges charitablie affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this poynt, then your ſelues (Right worſhipfull) amongeſt whome wee maye heare the Iudge himſelfe giuing ſentence of death to the bodye, with ſuch exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and comforts that may giue hope of life to the ſoule: not vnlike the skilfull Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> herein, which applie gentle and pleaſaunt fomentations to the member, that by theyr cutting and launcing is in paine.</p>
                  <p>There are two names (ſayeth <hi>Auſten) Homo: peccator:</hi> The man: and the offender: <hi>quòd peccator eſt, corripe:</hi> correct the offender: <hi>quòd homo eſt, miſerere:</hi> but pittie the man. In this reſpect the mariners that were appoynted to proceede to the execution of <hi>Ionas,</hi> found<note place="margin">Ionas. 1.</note> guiltie by lotte, were much to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for their obedience to GOD, and compaſſion to the partie condemned. For when they are about to caſt him into the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:26599:62"/> ſea, they breake out into this affectionate prayer: <hi>O Lorde, lay not vpon vs innocent bloud: for thou haſt done as pleaſed thee:</hi> which prayer, ſo well tempered with iuſtice, and mercie, may well beſeeme all men in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, when they ſit vpon life and death, and the ſearch or puniſhment of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
                  <p>If we ſhall enter into a more ſtrict exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of theſe three wordes, <hi>Eſtabliſh iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the gate,</hi> wee ſhall finde three things in them. Firſt, that there bee a ſettled habite in the diſtributers of iudgement: it muſt bee eſtabliſhed: Secondly, that it bee gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallye adminiſtred, without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: <hi>Iudgement is a common good.</hi> Thirdly, that the courſe of the ſame be practiſed in a publike place of free reſort, <hi>In the gate.</hi> It is not onelye ſome ſingle action which the Lorde vrgeth, but a continuall exerciſe and practiſe of iudgement. It is not enough to doe ſome things iuſtlie, at ſome times, and vpon ſome occaſions: but the ſtreames of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice muſt continuallie flowe, as from the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine heade of a ſounde conſcience. It is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> a moſt wicked King, that hee performed one poynt of iuſtice vpon a corrupt Iudge: but one ſwallow makes no ſommer.</p>
                  <p>That vngodly Iudge in the Goſpel did once
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26599:63"/> right for a widow, that ouercame his accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med delayes, with her importunate outcries:<note place="margin">Luke. 18.</note> the diuell himſelfe (they ſay) is good to ſome bodie: although it be againſt his will and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. And did not <hi>Pilate</hi> extende ſome poynts of iuſtice towards our Sauiour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 27. 24.</note> arraigned before him? Did he not pronounce him to be a <hi>iuſt man?</hi> did he not proteſt for his innocencie, that <hi>he found no fault in him?</hi> And<note place="margin">John. 19. 4.</note> yet behold againſt his ſpeach, and conſcience, he deliuereth him to be <hi>put to death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe to haue had ſome ſhadowes, but no ſtabilitie of truth or iuſtice in him.</p>
                  <p>A Magiſtrate that hath neither knowledge, nor conſcience (and accordingly, dooth not practiſe himſelfe in the courſe of iudgement) ſeemeth to be naked in the gate, although hee be clothed in ſcarlet: therefore he muſt ſuite himſelfe, and adorne his place and perſon with equitie, and diligence: as <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>I put on iuſtice, and it couered me; iudgement</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 29. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>was as a robe, and a crowne.</hi> So was he attired in iuſtice, as in a comely garment, couering all his parts. The cloke that hangeth vpon one ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is quickly blowne away, and ſome ſhreds and peeces of iudgement onely, are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſhew the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> true properties of a iuſt and vpright gouernour. <hi>Righteouſneſſe is to be put on as a girdle about the loynes, to gird all other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> to keepe them round and cloſe, and euen
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26599:63"/> on all parts: yet muſt it not be like the girdle, that ſaggeth &amp; be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth it ſelfe to that ſide, where the purſe and the money hangeth, not incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the right hand or to the left, to the rich or to the poore, but equally and indifferently<note place="margin">2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> bent to all alike. And this is the ſecond note of importance, whereby the nature of that which here is called iudgement, is declared. For iudgement muſt generally be diſtributed: it is not to giue the offender puniſhment only: but to yelde defence to the innocent and help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. And therfore in the holy ſcriptures when<note place="margin">Iſai. 1. 17.</note> we reade that the fatherles are to be iudged, and the poore, then we vnderſtand they are to be defended &amp; relieued againſt their aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. When the wicked are to be iudged: that<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 2. 4.</note> iudgement is vengeance and puniſhment to be inflicted vpon them according to their deſerts. And laſtly this refuge for the poore, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the vngodly muſt be in the gate pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that all goodnes and vpright dealing may finde fauour countenance &amp; maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce openly: that iudgement be not interrupted but eſtabliſhed, and that it flowe plentifully with a ſetled courſe, not being <hi>bitter like worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos. 5. 7.</note> to the meeke and innocent. And further that wholſome lawes being carefully enacted, may be as faithfully executed to the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods true ſeruice, the maintenance of the Princes dignitie vnder God, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26599:64"/> of Gods people in peace, godlyneſſe and all honeſtie.</p>
                  <p>This mention of the gate is not in vaine: for it teacheth vs that the Iudges &amp; Rulers ſate o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in a common place to heare and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all matters that were brought. The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are manifeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> namely, that iuſtice might glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſhine, and ſhewe it ſelfe in publike to the cheating vp of all faithfull hearts, and open ſhame and ignominie of euil workes. And that not only citizens, but cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trymen, forreiners, &amp; ſtrangers, might haue free acceſſe without da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger<note place="margin">Pet. Mart<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Jud. 5.</note> or diſturbance by any locall priuiledges. Beſides, the exerciſe of iudgement in the gate &amp; open place, might terrifie thoſe that had miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe in their harts, preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly <hi>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geance</hi> to their eyes, &amp; terror to their guiltie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences.</p>
                  <p>The conſideration of this place muſt needes put vs in minde of the Lords great benefit to vs continued: in that he hath ſo graciouſly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that our gates, and publike Courts of Iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice haue neither bin ſhut vp for feare of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, nor peſtered with warres &amp; violence; that<note place="margin">Zechar. 2. 7.</note> our Country is inhabited <hi>as Ieruſalem without walles:</hi> that our Caſtels bearing only the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent titles of warre, are become for the moſt part ruinous by long peace, &amp; courts where peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are executed: that our halberds are rather enſignes of honour and ornament, then weapons of neceſſitie.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:26599:64"/> 
                     <hi>Deborah,</hi> that mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> triumphed that<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> in her time <hi>the townes were inhabited, the people might goe to the gates for iudgement:</hi> and ſuch peace vnder the gouernement of a woman had the <hi>Land for fortie yeares.</hi> Of the like or greater<note place="margin">Verſ. 31.</note> benefits of peace, people, &amp; iudgements may our victorious Mother reioyce, <hi>&amp; ſet her hearte</hi> (as <hi>Deborah</hi> did) <hi>vpon the gouernours of Iſrael &amp;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>on them that are willing amongſt the people;</hi> to ſtir them vp to praiſe the Lord, for victories, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, &amp; continuance of peace, aboue the <hi>ſpace of forty yeares already: By thy good pleaſure (O Lord) &amp; to thy glory be theſe yeares doubled;</hi> of life to our <hi>Deborah,</hi> &amp; of peace to our <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But let vs returne to the gates of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t there practiſed in the time of <hi>Amos.</hi> All was not in frame belike, becauſe the Lord ſo earneſtly dealeth to haue iuſtice eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſhed, as though it were decayed, &amp; ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> It was euen ſo: when the Lord looked for iudgement, <hi>behold oppreſſion: for righteouſnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a crying. Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was turned backward, iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice ſtood a farre off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> truth was falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſtreets,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 59. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>quity could not enter, he that refrained from euil, made himſelfe a prey. The Lord knew their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, &amp; mighty ſins: they afflicte the iuſt, they take rewards, &amp; they oppreſſe the poore in the gate.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.12.</note> Therefore amend your waies (ſaith the Lord) eſtabliſh iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: let not vngodlines ſit in the place of iuſtice, any longer.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:26599:65"/>
                  <p>Shall we take a viewe of that which moſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted their ſtate, and ouerthroweth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all places whereit taketh foote? There was reſpect of perſons, a gainefull cauſe was ſooner heard, &amp; had more fauour, then trueth in <hi>form a pauperis.</hi> The <hi>righteous were ſolde for</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos. 2. 6. cap. 4. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>ſiluer, the poore for ſhooes. The great men were as kyne of Baſhan, full fedde, oppreſſing the poore, deſtroying the needy, and ſaying to their maiſters; Bring and let vs drinke.</hi> As though couetous Lawyers, ſhould ſerue the turnes of vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Landlords, in oppreſſing their poore te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants: and then call for the price of iniquity, to drinke and make themſelues merry with the teares of the widowe, the ſweate &amp; the bloud of the poore and oppreſſed. Then is the eſtate moſt deſperate, when the lawes are ſtretched to ſerue mens luſts, when priuate iniuries ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the countenance of the Court, and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the gate. When (as in <hi>Micahs</hi> time) <hi>To make good for the the euill of their hands: the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Micah. 7, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Prince aſketh, and the Iudge iudgeth for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: therefore the great man ſpeaketh out the corruption of his ſoule: and ſo they wrappe it vp</hi> ſaith <hi>Micah:</hi> as a filthy thing in a faire clout.</p>
                  <p>The Lord knowing that no wine was ſo da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to Princes, as the ſwallowing of giftes to make the magiſtrate dronke, and forget the equitie of cauſes: &amp; that no trayne was ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26599:65"/> to vndermine, and blowe vp the ſeat of iudgement, as thoſe traines of ſecret briberies, hath ſet downe this precept grounded vpon true experience; <hi>Thou ſhalt take no giftes: for gifts doe blinde the wiſe: and peruert the wordes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 23. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>of the righteous.</hi> Let no man reply, as though a man might purſe the rewards of the ſuiters: and his eyes ſee neuer the worſe, to doe Iuſtice: for the Lord ſaith, it is impoſſible but gifts wil <hi>blind the eyes of the wiſe:</hi> how much more of the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh? they will peruert the <hi>wordes of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:</hi> how much more of the couetous? and of him that will <hi>doe wronge for a morſell of breade?</hi> his conſcience being gulled with cuſtome of ſinne and iniuſtice?</p>
                  <p>It is not enough then to waſhe our handes from taking rewardes againſt the innocent: but hee muſt not ſell right, nor make marchandize of equitie. Hee that playeth a marchaunt of iuſtice, executeth iuſtice, but vniuſtly, ſaith<note place="margin">Philo de magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrat, delig.</note> 
                     <hi>Philo:</hi> he ſelleth that for a reward, that he ſhould afford <hi>grati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rem natura pulchram, deformem efficit:</hi> he blemiſheth a thing that is naturally beautifull: he hurteth the partie, whom hee ſhould helpe: taketh from him that hath the wrong alreadie, and getteth a bad cuſtome, that his hands and heart will linger after giftes more then attend to doe right. For giftes be<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> as birdlime, they intangle the winges, &amp; make that the receiuer is not his owne man, but ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:26599:66"/> in awe of the giuer.</p>
                  <p>The Lord knoweth what metall a man is made of, and therfore to keepe his conſcience ſound, and vncrackt, &amp; to keepe the ballance of iuſtice vpright, without leaning and tilting to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uieſt end, he wil haue no ſuch tentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of iniuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice admitted. <hi>Salomon</hi> knew the force of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? when he likeneth it to <hi>a pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtone, that</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>proſpereth which way ſoeuer it is turned:</hi> as though he ment it to be the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> ſo much in requeſt, &amp; ſo ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in effects, And indeede it makes court for a man in this world, <hi>&amp; bringeth</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prouerb. 18. 16. Prouerb. 29. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>him beforegreat me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but yet, by iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try maintained, &amp; a man receiuing gifts, deſtroyeth it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Thebans</hi> were heathens, and yet percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing<note place="margin">Plutar. in Iſid.</note> the inconueniences of receiuing rewards: painted their Iudges without hands; to ſignifie that they ſhould be no receiuers: an eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if Iudges were but images: but the Lord pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferres<note place="margin">Exod. 18. 21.</note> to his ſeates of Iudgement, <hi>ſuch as hate couetouſneſſe,</hi> becauſe they ſhould neither haue greedy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, nor rauenous harts after the prey; though for the purſuite of euil, &amp; cheriſhing the good, they ſhould be wel prouided of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both.</p>
                  <p>But gifts do not only conſiſt in taking with the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, of the rich: for he that reſpecteth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,<note place="margin">Prou. 28. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>will do wrong for a morſell of bread, for hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls of barlie, &amp; ſell the righteous for shooes:</hi> nay for leſſe than this, for ſome popular praiſe, for the breath of mens mouths, to get ſome fauour
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26599:66"/> of the poore, as well as of the rich.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Felix</hi> a corrupt Iudge fiſheth after money to be giuen him by <hi>Paul,</hi> for his deliuerance, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſendeth for him &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muneth with him of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: when he ſees no money come, though hee perceiueth his innocency, yet he <hi>leaueth him</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 24. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>bound,</hi> to make ſome aduantage by him, if not by money, yet to get a <hi>poore fauour</hi> at the <hi>Iewes</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d at the leaſt. The deſire of praiſe doth much: but the hope of gaine, and a gift in the boſome blindeth the eyes, charmeth the tongue, raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the affections, ſeareth vp the conſcience, turneth all things vp ſide downe, altereth the caſe, &amp; maketh that which is right to day, wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to morrow. Many in this aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly hauered of that famous Orator <hi>Demoſt hones,</hi> &amp; of that trip hee was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in, to his perpetual ſhame: for the firſt day he dealt moſt veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly againſt the <hi>Mileſian</hi> Ambaſſadors, the ſecond day he appears again but in another likenes; his neck is wrapped and<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> his cheeks muffled, as one that would ſhewe an excuſe before hand of his ſilence, by reaſon of his diſeaſe, which he would haue ſuppoſed to be <hi>Angina:</hi> the quinzie, or the mumps: the people perceiuing his ſwelling &amp; ſilence, to be but the blowes of a ſecret bribe, termed his griefe to be <hi>Arge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tangina,</hi> as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſay not the quinzy but the coyn-ſec, &amp; ſiluer mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ps. I truſt this diſeaſe be not amongſt our Orators (amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt the better ſort, I know it is deteſted) yet ſome we hear ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26599:67"/> of ſome ſuch ſodaine crampe in their tongues, by reaſon that they haue failed their clyent at his greateſt need in preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or ſpeach, vnder ſome pretence or other: take heede: for there is no greater wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to publike iuſtice, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate conſcience or credit, then to play vpon both hands, and betray the truſt of him that dependeth vpon your patronage.</p>
                  <p>But is it not lawfull for Lawiers, or learned Counſailors to receiue fees? I come not to marre the market, nor to take away the hire of the labourer: they may receiue their fees, if they giue their counſell, although not on both ſides. <hi>Saint Auſten</hi> doth rule this caſe, &amp; teacheth who ſhould be receiuers in the courts of iuſtice, and who not. A Iudge muſt not ſell, no not <hi>Iuſtum iudicium:</hi> iuſt iudgement: nor a<note place="margin">Ad Mac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>don.</note> witneſſe <hi>verum teſtimonium,</hi> no not true wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: much leſſe falſhood. For the Iudge is to hold the ballance equally betweene both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and therefore muſt not be ſwayed with gifts: the witneſſe muſt ſpeake the trueth indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently. But for the honorable Iudges, there muſt be penſions of honor, eſtate and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, aſſigned by the Prince, or els in common not depending on the ſuiters. <hi>Nehemiah had prepared for him, daily an oxe, and ſixe choſen</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nehemiah. 5. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>ſheepe, birds and wine in abundance:</hi> although in the diſtreſſe of the people, he required not the breade of the gouernour: nor ſuch large allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26599:67"/> But for an aduocate it is lawfull (ſaith <hi>Auſten</hi>) to priſe his paines, and for a counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor to take reward for his learned counſell of the ſuiter which retaineth him: the weight of whoſe cauſe he muſt vrge to the vttermoſt of his knowledge, as being an eye to his clyent that can not wel diſcerne his owne right, and a mouth for the dumbe, that cannot open his mouth in the gate. And yet ſuch counſell muſt he giue, as tendeth not to the ſtopping of the courſe of Iuſtice, with crooked ſhifts and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes: but his counſell and pleading (as you can tell beſt your ſelues) muſt be, rather to giue light out of darkneſſe, then to caſt ſmoake, &amp; cloude ouer the light, rather to vnfolde then obſcure the matter, entering rather a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a conflict; that as two ſtones ſtrooke together the fire flyes out: ſo the wiſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Counſellors arguing the caſe, the trueth may appeare, the Iurie may vnderſtand, the Iudge proceed to ſentence; &amp; Iudgement may be exalted in the gate.</p>
                  <p>As all good ordinances and benefits of the Lord may be abuſed by the corruption of men: ſo may our peace, and place of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be defaced, either by officers or ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</p>
                  <p>By officers from the higheſt to the loweſt, if there be not a hatred of ſinne, and loue of vertue fixed in the conſcience: when officers
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26599:68"/> will ſuffer corruption, and ſuiters offer corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what wickedneſſe is not then bredde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them? When <hi>Dauid</hi> began to ſing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and iudgement, he firſt cleanſed his houſe,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſal. 101.</note> vowed to <hi>walke vprightly himſelfe,</hi> and to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire out of his family, the ſlanderer, the proud, the deceiptfull perſon, the lyer, and all that ranke: and then he proceedeth and threatneth <hi>to deſtroy all the wicked of the Land.</hi> If greate mens houſes were ſo purged, the citie of God would the ſooner be cleanſed, and the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the better be furthered. It is daungerous for the head when the eyes be deceiptfull: when the inferiour officers and agents be as falſe ſpectacles, to miſſe informe the conceipt, and make that which is ſtraight, ſeeme croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. What a diſgrace of Iuſtice, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is it, when attendants and officers bee like the horſe-leeches daughters, crying euer<note place="margin">Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 30.</note> giue, giue, neuer ſatisfied? or when they ſhewe themſelues light or vncomely, in geſture or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? The throne of <hi>Salomon</hi> had lyons carued<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>King. 7.</hi>
                     </note> about it, to declare a kinde of maieſty and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie in the very ſteppes: not apes, nor foxes, nor wolues; beaſtes that were eyther toyiſh, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptful, or rauenous after their prey: ſo ſhould greate mens ſeruants, and officers of Iuſtice be lyons in ſhewe for grauitie, yet harmeleſſe as thoſe Images about the ſeate of <hi>Salomon:</hi> rather terrible to them that ſtand aloufe, then hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:26599:68"/> to thoſe that haue occaſion to come neere.</p>
                  <p>That zealous and vpright Ruler <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other the abuſes of his predeceſſors the gouernours of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> taxeth this to haue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beene none of the ſmalleſt, that they themſelues were not onely ouerchargeable, but their ſeruants bare rule ouer the people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.<note place="margin">Nehemi. 5. 15.</note> As who doubteth but inferiour creatures wil be moſt imperious, when they haue but the cloath or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance of men in authoritie: if<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Sam. 2. 13.</hi>
                     </note> they may be ſuffered to make their owne game &amp; games. <hi>Elies</hi> boyes were more <hi>ſaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y with their fleſh-hookes,</hi> than became the ſons or ſeruantes of a holy man: they ſmarted for it themſelues:<note place="margin">1. Sam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. 13.</note> but their father alſo, and his houſe for euer <hi>was iudged beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe his ſons ran into a ſlaunder, and he ſtayed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not.</hi> Too many not only of the prieſts boyes, but temporall mens officers, being but hungry flies at the firſt, bite ſore, &amp; pinch neere, making that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint of the Lord in <hi>Iſay</hi> to be true: Children are extortioners of my people. I know that many godly fathers may haue wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſons, &amp; good maſters bad ſeruants. Our <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt</hi> had a theefe to his purſ-bearer: <hi>the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 12. 6. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> King. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>man of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>od Eliſeus, had Gehezi, a lyer:</hi> but he followed him at an inch, till hee found out his priuie brokeage and caſt him off for an hypocrite. It is a worthy anſwer made by the heatheniſh prince <hi>Tiberius,</hi> to a polling cuſtomer of his<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that thought to haue highly
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26599:69"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:26599:69"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:26599:70"/> pleaſured his Prince with racking his ſubiects, &amp; exacting great ſummes: <hi>Meum tonderi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>im in Tib.</note> 
                     <hi>volo, non deglubi:</hi> I will haue my ſheepe ſhorne &amp; not fleyed. It is the propertie of theſe vnderhand dealers, to pretend great huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry for their maiſters, and double diligence in their ſeruice: vnder which colour they practiſe their iniquitie without checke or controlment. But becauſe it is not for mee to ſpeake againſt theſe, except I haue a ſound warrant, I referre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to that threatning of the Lord in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zephanie</hi> (where the Lord ſaith) <hi>I will vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ophan. 1. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>all ſuch as are cloathed with ſtrange apparrell, &amp; thoſe that daunce vpon the threſhold ſo proudly, which fill their maſters houſes by cruelty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt.</hi> Wherein we beholde their apparell to be ſtrange for faſhion, their gate more like daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing then going, their place to be at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance, and threſhold of their maſters dore; no man may approch but by their admiſſion: their geſture to be full of pride, their gettings to be great, for they ſtore themſelues, &amp; their maſters houſes: the meanes to be wicked, by deceipt and crueltie: and the redreſſe of theſe inconueniences to be referred to the viſitation of the Lord himſelfe. <hi>I will viſit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As officers, ſo ſuters doe many times vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine the frame of ſacred iudgement in the gate. Suitors are eyther ſuch as ſeeke for Law or Iuſtice: or ſuch as owe ſuite or ſeruice for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:26599:70"/> tryall of right, as Iurors and witneſſes. As for men of our profeſſion, I take them rather to be beholders, then actors, except it be in this place: And (vnder reformation be it ſpoken) extraordinarie men rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fit Ordinaries to holde the booke and the candle to an old tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>want, that all his life time hath liued without booke.</p>
                  <p>Touching the ſuitors therefore that ſeeke for reliefe, and righting of wrongs; euen they by their crooked &amp; ſiniſter dealings, by their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious actions, and bad handling their matters with additions of ſubtiltie, and priuate corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may poyſon and trouble the wholſome ſtreames of Iuſtice, which ſhould refreſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and others. Of theſe I haue ſpoken large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not long ſince out of this place, in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the moſt, here now aſſembled: for this time let them remember <hi>Salomons</hi> caueat: <hi>Goe not forth haſtily to ſtrife, leaſt thou knowe not what to doe in the end thereof, when thy neighbor</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 25. 8. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>hath put thee to ſhame, debate thy matters with thy neighbour.</hi> As though he counſelled to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the end before a man beginne: and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound all controuerſies at home, if it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and vſe the lawe as men vſe Phiſicke for neceſſitie, not wantonneſſe. Againſt theſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and raſh ſuiters, that ſeeke rather for lawe then right: no ſuch approued remedie, as the countenance of a Iudge like a Northern wind<note place="margin">Pro. 25. 23.</note>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:26599:71"/> blowing them away from the ſeat of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Next vnto theſe ſuiters, are ſuch as owe ſuite and appearance, by reaſon of ſome good ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie of wealth, aboue the common ſort. Our law intendeth theſe to be as pettie Iudges, and therfore it behooueth them to learne wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the knowledge of equitie aboue the vulgar people. It is true that (as the wiſe man ſpeaketh) <hi>ſuch as only hold the plough, or meddle with their cattell, or follow their handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ecclus. 38. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>are not aſked their iudgement in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of the people:</hi> but you are they that can labour, and yet neede not, at all turnes: and therefore your ſufficiencie of liuelihoode and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the lawes of the Realme doe call for ſome good education of your children, ability in your ſelues to vnderſtand, and conceiue the order and courſe of Iuſtice. If the lawe make you Iudges, the Lord telleth you that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt, you muſt be wiſe: that you<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note> may ſee, not with other mens eyes, but your owne. Now it is pitifull to beholde how vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerently many take their oathes, how ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they regard them: for the moſt part it is made but a matter of forme and cuſtome. As they take the ſame oath with their foreman, ſo commonly they beleeue as he beleeues, thinke as he ſpeakes, without further examining the circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces: or els they regard the priuie ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:26599:71"/> of a forſworne bailif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; follow him as a falſe guide: or in the preiudice, &amp; ſtubborn par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality of their own affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, without reaſon or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe, dwell in an opinion: that though they be braied as oatmeale in a morter with a<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 17. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> peſtell, yet will not their foliſhnes leaue them. And euen by theſe meanes, is the courſe of iudgement hindered in the gate.</p>
                  <p>After theſe, follow the witneſſes, which ſpeake indeed before them: for witneſſe muſt go before verdict. Theſe of all other muſt be vpright and indifferent, &amp; ſpeake the trueth ſincerely. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, by prohibiting men from <hi>bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring falſe witneſſe,</hi> ſet down that very phraſe in his ſpeach, as being the higheſt offence that by the tongue might be committed againſt our neighbour. Theſe muſt know that they ſpeake before God: for they informe, &amp; aſſiſt with their euidence, <hi>ne quid Iudex (quia inſpector cordis non</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> 
                     <hi>eſt) Iudica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do erret:</hi> leaſt the Iudge (being no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the hart) ſhould erre in Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Theſe being guides to others, in the finding out of the trueth, if they ſhal faile, may miſſelead Iudges, Iurie, counſel, right &amp; al. Of al that reſort to the place of Iuſtice, none doth ſo prophane, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuouſly abuſe the ordinance of God, as a falſe witnes: <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>he mocketh at iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prou.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; ſwalloweth iniquitie.</hi> He laugheth in his ſleeue, to ſee that he can delude ſo many graue wiſe and learned men aſſembled.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:26599:72"/>
                  <p>I greatly feare that iudgement after this ſort, by ſuch kinde of people is made but a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kery in our daies. For what ſay ſome being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts amongſt vs? If it ſtand vpon the proofe of mine aduerſarie, I am gone: entending that a man of a large conſcience may haue proofe and witneſſe for any thing. There were a kind of heretikes, called <hi>Priſcillianiſtes:</hi> which gaue theſe precepts, <hi>Iura, periura, &amp;c.</hi> ſweare, and forſweare: but it was to auoide perſecution, &amp; to couer their owne filthie abſurdities. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine heathens vſed to ſweare (as they ſaide) with their tongue, but not with their heart: but others that knewe not God, yet condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this prophane excuſe and cloke of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall I call our falſe ſwearers, that for a friend, or a maſter, or a peece of money (pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing more then friend and maſter, or GOD himſelfe with them) will not refuſe to iuſtifie any thing vpon their oath? Theſe <hi>Libertines</hi> of our age, worſe than heretikes, more wicked than the reffuſe of the heathens, dare in the preſence of God, before the ſeate of iudgement (hauing their diueliſh falſehood co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradicted by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie oath many times, their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces gal led with euidence of the trueth it ſelfe, terrified by the warnings of the zealous Iudge) yet ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broach a falſe and forged teſtimonie to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowing of al iuſt proceeding in the courſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:26599:72"/> of iudgement. I know theſe fellowes are of great antiquitie, though neuer growne ſo ſhameleſſe as now. <hi>Moſes prouided legem talio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, for them that ſhould beare falſe witneſſe. The Iudges,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>ſhall make diligent inquiſition,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>and if a falſe witneſſe be found, it ſhall be done to him, as he thought to doe to his brother: an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth.</hi> As that decree by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> againſt falſe witneſſes, argueth that in his time, ſuch vngodlineſſe was feared. ſo the plot of <hi>Ieſabell</hi> (that, writing to the Iudges, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them to ſet vp two <hi>wicked men, ſonnes of Belial,</hi> or vnthrifts, as ſome tranſlation hath, ſuborned witneſſes agaynſt the life of innocent <hi>Naboth</hi>) manifeſtly ſheweth, that this abuſe was both knowne and practiſed by the higher powers, who ſhould rather haue ſought out and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſuch deſperate vnthrifts, and <hi>children of Belial,</hi> then made vſe of their falſhood. But the like cuſtomers were imployed agaynſt Chriſt, agaynſt <hi>Steuen:</hi> and the like trecherie poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth our common knights of the Poſte, ſuch as being banquerupt of their goods, hauing loſt both credite and honeſtie where they are knowne, now ſet to ſale their conſcience to the world, and their ſoules to the diuell. <hi>Iuuenal,</hi> a heatheniſh Satyriſt, in his time derided ſuch<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> looſe companions, for betaking themſelues to ſuch profeſſed villanie; and wiſheth them ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be brokers of old ſtuffe: <hi>Hoc ſatius quàm
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:26599:73"/> ſi dicas ſub iudice, vidi, quod non vidiſti.</hi> Any baſe trade were better then to ſay before a Iudge, <hi>I ſaw, that which thou neuer ſaweſt. Faciant Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Aſiani</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quam &amp; Cappadoces fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant equiteſque Britanni.</note>: Let the Aſian knights, renowned for periurie, and falſe euidence, exerciſe that profeſſed trecherie. He thought it a diſgrace for Romanes. And wee may thinke ſuch damned practiſes vnworthie to bee named amongeſt Chriſtians, except it be with reproofe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation.</p>
                  <p>If any ſuch vngodly wretches flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their ſinne, ſuppoſing by their ſecrete carriage to eſcape, let them remember that the Lord threatneth <hi>to be a ſwift witneſſe againſt</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Malach. 1. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>falſe ſwearers:</hi> and to ſend <hi>a flying booke, whoſe contents ſhall be a curſe, to enter into the houſe of</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zacha.</hi> 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>him that ſweareth falſly, and there remaine till it conſume houſe, timber, ſtones and all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus haue we vnfolded thoſe conditions at large, which the prophet fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord doth vrge to the people, in this briefe abridgement; <hi>Hate the euill, loue the good, eſtabliſh iudgement in the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi> You haue heard that the Lord requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth holy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> affections, iuſt actions; a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience led by knowledge, to the hatred of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, &amp; loue of the good: an vpright conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion exerciſed in the workes of iuſtice, &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, holineſſe and iudgement, by euery man from the higheſt to the loweſt, in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:26599:73"/>
                  <p>Wee haue ſeene the defectes and decayes of iudgement, and how they are to bee repaired and amended, that Gods people may haue a ſure refuge from all iniuries and oppreſſions. And to this end is euerie man to meditate vpon his vocation and place, firſt in the Church and ſtate of Chriſtianitie, ſecondly in the Common wealth; and to ſtudie how his conſcience, and actions thereupon grounded, may turne to the maintenance of religion, vertue, and peace, and to the wracke and confuſion of ſinne and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions. <hi>Singulus quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> homo, eſt vt vna litera</hi>
                     <note place="margin">De ciuit. Dei lib. 4. cap. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>in ſermone, &amp; quaſi elementum in ciuitate,</hi> ſayth ſaint <hi>Auſten:</hi> Euery man is as one letter in the ſpeach, and Alphabet; one element and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Citie or Countrie. The higheſt in dignitie, &amp; deepeſt in skill, as reuerend Iudges, worthy Gentlemen, learned Counſellers, are as vowels: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urors and witneſſes, as halfe vowels, to ſpeake when they are ſpoken to, &amp; to ſound ſomthing with others, nothing with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. <hi>Mutes</hi> there bee that cannot ſpeake in their owne cauſe: whoſe ſilence is to be aſſiſted by the ſound of others, that are charged to open<note place="margin">Prou. 31.</note> their mouth for the dumbe. Dipthongs there be too many; double tongues, which breath out hote and cold; theſe marr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the conſort of iudgement, and harmonie of truth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are to be razed out of the row of a Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Alphabet. To conclude, if all hearts be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:26599:74"/> for the aduauncement of Gods kingdom, and all hands ſtrong &amp; couragious to eſtabliſh the righteouſneſſe thereof (both in the true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Lord, as alſo in the preſeruation of his people) then doth the Lord of hoſts promiſe for his part a truce, and peace to be extended to vs, as to his intirely beloued ſubiects.</p>
                  <p>Hauing thus declared what conditions the Lord expecteth: now remaineth to ſhew the Content of his promiſe, and mercie propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for his part. <hi>It may be the Lord will be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the remnant of Ioſeph.</hi> Seeing that if there be any default it will be on our part: therefore haue we beate moſt vpon this poynt, that we firſt performe theſe articles required: for (as the Lord ſaith in <hi>Malachie) Bring all your tithes into my ſtore-houſe, that there may be meate in my houſe, and proue me now herewith, if I will not powre vpon you a bleſſing without meaſure.</hi> So, if we would bring the firſt fruits of our wiſdom, zeale and courage, that there might be iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prouided as meate in due ſeaſon for the reliefe of Gods people: proue him, if he will not be mercifull vnto vs, aboue all that we are able to aske or thinke.</p>
                  <p>This phraſe of ſpeach, <hi>It may be;</hi> implieth no vncertaintie, on Gods behalfe: neither doth it teach to doubt in the Lords goodneſſe: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it referreth all to his owne good pleaſure, which neuer faileth them that turne to him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:26599:74"/> But as the Iſraelites, in regard of their manifold tranſgreſſions, and many euident to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods anger burning towards them: in regard of the ſmall remnant of people left, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but as ſome two legges, and a peece of an<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Amos.</hi> 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ear, reſcued by the ſhepheard, out of <hi>the mouth of the Lion:</hi> might conceiue ſome vnlikelihood of their reſtauration: ſo we (beloued in the Lord) caſting our eyes vpon the infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our ſinnes, beholding them as redde as skarlet, and hearing them clamorous in the<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.</note> eares of God and men: beholding his ſworde<note place="margin">Ezech. 21. 10.</note> ready furbiſhed to ſmite: remembring the loſſe of many ſound Church-men, religious Fathers, graue Counſellers, deepe ſtates-men, vpright Iudges, valiant warriours, worthie luſticiaries, which in ſhort time we haue ſuſtained: may perhaps in a ſodaine paſſion breake out, and crie with the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> in a viſion: <hi>Spare (O Lord God) I beſeech thee: who ſhall raiſe vp Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Amos.</hi> 7. 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>for it is ſmall.</hi> And yet againe, as the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites beholding an outſtretched arme of a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull father, an almightie power of him that is the Lord of Hoſts: remembring his deliuerance to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> their father, contrarie to expectation: and ſeeing yet a Remnant ſtill reſerued, of ſuch as may be inſtruments of their recouerie, might lift vp their heades in hope of their proſperitie to be reſtored. So we conſidering the Lordes mercie, ſealed to vs by many fauors: the Goſpel
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:26599:75"/> yet continued: <hi>the barres of our gates made ſtrong: the light of our Iſrael vnquenched</hi> by<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>al. 147. 13. Sam. 21. 17.</note> preſeruation of the Lordes annoynted: behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a ſupply of faithfull Counſellers; a tythe of graue and learned fathers, godly and painfull Miniſters: the ſeates of iudgement furniſhed with men as renowmed for wiſdome and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, as in any age; the Countrie repleniſhed with many zealous gentlemen, prepared both to keepe the peace, and <hi>build the wall of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ehemiah. 4.</note> with <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and armed alſo againſt the ſodaine enemies of God, and the realme, at all aſſayes: perceyuing an <hi>holy ſeede,</hi> being as the <hi>ſubſtance of a tree that hath caſt her leaues,</hi> a <hi>ſprinkling of true O liues</hi> remaining amongſt vs<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſai. 6. 13.</note> vngathered: <hi>a freſh care springing</hi> vp in the nurſeries of our land, for religion and all good artes; ſome houſes of learning erected; libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of mute maſters reſtored from their ruines;<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Sam. 19. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>amen. 4. 7.</hi>
                     </note> many good <hi>Samuels</hi> gouerning <hi>Naioth,</hi> and <hi>the ſchooles of the Prophets,</hi> many pretious <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarites,</hi> as <hi>the poliſhed Saphires ſhining.</hi> If they<note place="margin">Amos. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 12. Reuel. 17. 4.</note> may be kept from the wine of that <hi>golden cup</hi> in the <hi>Reuelation:</hi> and not forbad by their parents to qroqhecie, and ſerue God in his miniſterie. Seeing, I ſay, ſuch meanes reſcrued, and ſparks of comfort ſhewing themſelues in this dark ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and knowing the Lords mercy in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing meanes of ſafetie, to thoſe whom he intendeth to deliuer: knowing his power in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:26599:75"/> his will by feeble meanes: we may yet haue ſome confidence that the Lord will take ſome longer truce, &amp; grant a larger time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance towards vs, ſuffering vs ſtill to eat the good things of our land, and enioy peace with godlineſſe and honeſtie. But who are we that we ſhould preſcribe vnto the Lord any condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? or ſtand vpon tearmes with him? It is beſt for vs to imitate thoſe valiant captaines of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who hauing ſet their men in aray, and readineſſe for battell, breake out into this cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious<note place="margin">2. Sam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10. 12.</note> exhortation. <hi>Be ſtrong, and let vs be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant for our people, and for the cities of our God: and let the Lord do that, which is good in his eyes.</hi> So now hauing placed euery man in his ranke and order, in the Church and Commonwealth, there remaineth onely this, that we (faſtening our eies vpon the Lord our ſtrength) be ſtrong and valiant in the hatred of euill, loue of the good, and in the aduauncement of iudgement, and righteouſneſſe in our gates: that the Lord may ſubſcribe to the continuance of our peace and felicitie, in ſuch particulars as it ſhall ſeeme good to his wiſdome, and Maieſtie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to whome being the King euerlaſting, immortall, inuiſible, and God onely wiſe, be honour and glorie for euer and euer,</p>
                  <closer>Amen.</closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
